<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of adhering to God; written by Albert the Great, Bishop of Ratisbon. Put into English by Sir Kenelme Digby, Kt. Also a conference with a lady about choyce of religion.</title>
            <title>De adhærendo Deo. English</title>
            <author>Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76020</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1529_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25226</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872087</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872087</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170053</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76020)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170053)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 195:E1529[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of adhering to God; written by Albert the Great, Bishop of Ratisbon. Put into English by Sir Kenelme Digby, Kt. Also a conference with a lady about choyce of religion.</title>
                  <title>De adhærendo Deo. English</title>
                  <author>Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280.</author>
                  <author>Digby, Kenelm, Sir, 1603-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 139, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman, at the Anchor in the New-Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654. [i.e. 1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: De adhærendo Deo.</note>
                  <note>"A conference with a lady about choyce of religion" by Sir Kenelm Digby has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb [the] 9: 1653."; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170053:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF Adhering to God; Written by <hi>Albert the Great,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ratisbon.</hi> Put into Engliſh by Sir <hi>Kenelme Digby,</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</p>
            <p>ALSO A Conference with a Lady about Choyce of <hi>RELIGION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Herring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> at the Anchor in the New-Exchange. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170053:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170053:2"/>
            <head>To the Lady DIGBY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen lately I was commanded out of England, I was ſo ſtreightened in time, that I was not able to carry any thing with me, beſides what I had about me. And the difficulties that my ſervants met with in following mee, and in bringing my carriages after me, made me remain here ſometimes in want of my ordinary attendants, and of ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries as I had dayly need of. I was not ſo ſenſible of any, as of the deprivation of my bookes: which in all fortunes I had ever ſound my beſt companions; and in whoſe converſation I as well profited, as pleaſed my ſelf. And therefore in all my journies (even the longeſt and moſt cumberſome) I have ever uſed to have a convenient ſtore of them with mee. I was now reduced to
<pb facs="tcp:170053:3"/>have none other by me, but a ſhort diſcourſe of <hi>Albert</hi> the great, concerning the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of a ſpiritual life; which at my ſetting forth from London, I had put into my pocket; invited thereto, by the dignity of the ſubject, the excellency of the author, and the ſmallneſſe of the bulk of it. I read it over with much delight; And judged it ſo profitable a work, that I deſired to impreſs the contents of it as deep as I could in my memory: and indeed to convert the whole treatiſe, into the very ſubstance of my ſoul, as hoping, it may one day ſerve mee for a rule to govern my poor devotions by; as far as my feeble eyes may be able to ſee by the light of ſo dazeling a ſunne.</p>
            <p>This occaſioned me to employ my ſelf in rendring in my own tongue, the expreſſions which this author had made in Latin. For I believe, ſcarce any ſtudy doth ſo vigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſt an other mans notions into the nouriſhment of ones own minde, as doth the tranſlating or the paraphraſing of them. And when I had done it, I deemed it one of the moſt profitable tasks (of ſo ſhort an one) that ever I had buſied myſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.
<pb facs="tcp:170053:3"/>Neither could I be content to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe unto my ſelfe alone ſo noble a feast: I deſired that my beſt friend ſhould ſhare with me in it: whoſe partaking with me in any good, I muſt ever account, the crowning and compleating of it, to me. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I preſently reſolved to ſend your La: a coppy of this diſcourſe: which I confeſſe, is much empayred and enfeebled by its change of habit. For to expreſſe the authors ſenſe with full weight, requireth alike know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as he had, of the matter he wrighteth of. And this is not to be acquired by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane induſtry, or dint of wit: but is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the unction of the holy Ghoſt; that is never wanting where it findeth due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and diſpoſitions on the creatures part. And in this, Myſtical Divinity dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from all other ſciences, that the right underſtanding of it, dependeth of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent faithfull practiſing it. Like as in divine truths, he that would ſee the light which ſhineth in them, muſt firſt beleive them. To converſe familiarly with the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God that is within us, requireth a total abſtraction from the hindring objects
<pb facs="tcp:170053:4"/>that are without us. And the various courſe in the world, that I have runne my ſelfe out of breath in, hath afforded me little means for ſolid recollection. Therefore it cannot be expected that I ſhould otherwiſe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend this holy Biſhops notions, and expreſſe them in my language; then as men uſe to frame apprehenſions upon hear-ſay of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treies they were never in; and afterwards deliver them to others. They who have bin there, will ſoon perceive great miſtakes in the others diſcourſes and deſcriptions. And ſo will your Ladyſhip (whom long, conſtant, practiſe hath rendred ſo profoundly knowing in this ſublime Science,) in this tranſlation, or rather ſhort Paraphraſe of mine. I have been fain to make it ſuch, becauſe I could not ſatisfie my ſelfe of rendring compleatly the authors ſenſe by a verbal tranſlation of his words. The compoſition of Authors are either forged in their fantaſy; or are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of their understanding; or are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of their affective part. All theſe (I conceive) do claim a different courſe to be taken in rendring them in another tongue.
<pb facs="tcp:170053:4"/>Thoſe of the firſt kinde do exact a ſtrict ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal tranſlation. For they ſpringing from notions that have their reſidence in the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and being barely of that low orbe: plain words, that have their lively pictures alſo there, do repreſent them adequately; And conſequently, in an other tongue, words of the ſame ſignification, do render them fully. But in compoſitions of deep judgement (in which the manners of expreſſion do inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate further meanings, then the meer words barely conſidered, do ſeem to imploy) one muſt uſe a far different method to render them with their due weight and force in an other language. One muſt firſt comprehend the fullneſſe of their ſenſe, and ſettle in ones own thoughts the ſame; and then deliver thoſe thoughts as compleatly and ſignificant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as one can, in ones own words and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of expreſſion. For want of doing which, wee ſee the best writers loſe exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their ſtrength and energy, when they are tranſlated by ſuch as confine themſelves grammatically to their authors words.</p>
            <p>This maketh <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſo lame, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:170053:5"/>bare in many tranſlations; <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſo obſcure and unpleaſant; <hi>Avicenna</hi> ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous; <hi>Virgil</hi> ſo ungracefull; and <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> himſelfe appear oftentimes but flat and dry. Much more this happeneth in affective expreſſion. Wee ſee how the ſame words that are extreamly moving, when they are ſpoken in paſſion by a lover, prove flat and cold, when an other perſon barely relateth them. And ſuch an effect as the manner of geſture and earneſtneſſe worketh in ſpeaking, the like doth the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of couching the ſenſe, and the phraſe, in writing. The Arcadia of Sr <hi>Philip Sidney</hi> (of whom I may ſay as St <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did of Homer, that he is paſſing ſweet and delightful, even in his vanities) though it be very faithfully tranſlated into other languages, in regard of grammatical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, yet it appeareth with little grace amongst forraigners, who cannot believe how ſtrangely that book uſeth to raiſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and paſſions in ſuch as read it in the original Engliſh. If this be ſo in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of ſuch affections as have but crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for their objects, how muſt it fare with
<pb facs="tcp:170053:5"/>thoſe which being fixed upon the Creator, do require a profound abſtraction of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; an admirable purity of heart in the readers, that they may have a right taſte of them. He that will render effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly the expreſſions of a ſoul burning with affections, muſt be endued with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a like temper. He knoweth that ſuch a one is not ſollicitous about his words: and that therefore he ought not to be ſcrupulous in weighing them. The underſtanding cannot look to the bottome of ſuch expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nor reliſh the ſweetneſſe that is in them. He muſt abound with affections in himſelfe, that would ſavour the language of affections ſpoken by an other. Hearts of this temper, are like the ſtrings of different lutes tuned alike, which move in both, though but one be touched. Now <hi>Alberts</hi> language in this treatiſe, being much of this ſtrain, I cannot be ſo partial to myſelf as to hope that my Engliſh arriveth near expreſſing the fulneſs of his ſenſe. I may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this occaſion ſay as St <hi>Thomas</hi> did, when he was deſired to comment <hi>Salomons</hi> mystical Song, as St <hi>Bernard</hi> before him
<pb facs="tcp:170053:6"/>had don (and with much more reaſon and juſtice;) If I had St <hi>Bernards</hi> ſpirit, I would make ſuch a comment as St <hi>Bernard</hi> did. He onely that hath the ſpirit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this illuminated Biſhop wrote, can fully comprehend and render his ſenſe in this divine and myſtical treatiſe. Therefore I muſt neceſſarily have fallen very ſhort in my tranſlation; ſince it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that I ſhould mak it ſpeak, but at that rate, as my ſelfe did firſt understand it.</p>
            <p>Beſides this improportion on my ſide; the Authors manner of delivering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath made my talke much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult. It is evident that he little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in what words or ſtile he expreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>He was ſo full of the matter, that he neglected the forme and dreſſe he put it in. And writing it in the nature of a ſummary remembrance, for his own uſe, and ſome other pious and intelligent perſons of his own order, his particular friends (ſor hee was a Dominican Fryar, before hee was made a Biſhop) hee conceived it ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:170053:6"/>for him to give but hints or notes of what he aymed at: which would preſently bring before them the whole ſequel of conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were compriſed under ſuch heads, and that he had often diſcourſed largely unto them. And the nature of ſuch a writing admitting frequent ſoddain tranſitions to new matter (or that may ſeem new, to one that ſeeth not the connection of it with what was ſaid before) it is very hard to worke ſuch a piece into an even contexture with one entire and continued thread. The courſe I took to wade as well as I could through theſe difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, was to endeavour out of what hee had ſaid, to raiſe my own thoughts to be as like unto his, as my weakneſſe could attain unto. And then I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied my ſelfe to expreſſe thoſe thoughts as ſignificantly as I could, in my own man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeech, upon the model he hath left; (in the mean time, departing as little as I could from his words, where I might follow them) and connecting the broken tranſitions, as I conceived they were
<pb facs="tcp:170053:7"/>connected in his minde, though they appear not ſo at the firſt ſight in the words that he hath uttered his conceptions by. Yet, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his being thus ſhort through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, he often repeateth the ſame thing (but ſtill with ſome addition and further expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the matter) to inculcate it the deeper: as is recorded of St <hi>Jo.</hi> the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt;</hi> who in his latter time, whenſoever he was deſired to preach, did still but repeat the ſame few words, by which he invited his auditors to the love that charity ordaineth. This ſheweth how the ſubſtance and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a ſpiritual life conſiſteth in a very narrow room. And therefore St <hi>Denis</hi> the Areopagit, who is ſo diffuſe in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, is moſt ſuccinct in his myſtical divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: as having for its ſubject but that only one thing which in the Goſpel our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour telleth us is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>The end of all ſpiritual exerciſe, is but to love God with the whole activity of ones ſoul; And the expediteſt way to bring one thereunto, is to baniſh all other affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and inclinations from the heart, and all other thoughts from ones minde. The
<pb facs="tcp:170053:7"/>impreſſions which creatures make in one are like boiſterous windes, that wrinkling the face of a water (and peradventure rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing mudde in it) do deface and keep out thoſe images, which would ſhine in it, if it were calme and ſmooth. He that can wiſely keep his ſoul from adhering to any thing without him, ſhall finde his creator ſhine gloriouſly within him. It is the eminence of ſuperior things to ſend alwaies emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from them, for the bettering of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ones; if they exclude them not. So we ſee the ſun ſends his beams into every corner of the hemiſphere, if nothing ſhut them out. Open the windowes and draw the curtains, and the chamber that before was darke will then immediately grow lightſome. The ſhutters and ſcreenes which keep out the divine ſun from illuminating and warming our ſouls, are the images of creatures, that reſide in them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Authors main endeavour conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in adviſing and preſſing a totall denu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation from all ſuch. Hence proceedeth this frequent iteration, and inculcating of this document.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170053:8"/>
            <p> Yet he doth no ſo abſolutely exclude all corporall ſhapes out of the imagination, but that he adviſeth and exhorteth all men to exerciſe themſelves in the continual medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Saviours paſſion. Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compoſed of two natures; ſpiritual and corporall; and the corporall part having in this life gotten the ſtart of the other, it is impoſſible for us, to tie up our ſenſes from all commerce with materiall objects: and very hard for us to keep ſome of them from making ſmart impreſſions in our fantaſie; which is as it were the window that letteth in outward lights to the ſoul. For the moſt part they are falſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull ones. And the onely means to be ſecure from ſuch, is to fill that ſtore-houſe with ſafe materials; and than were it but through want of room, it will not admit of others. Of all theſe, the perfecteſt, and indeed the moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to our nature, and conſequently the most powerfull to move us, is the hiſtory of Christs life and paſſion. We ſee that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven tragedies and Romances, of perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture feigned ſubjects (or at leaſt that
<pb facs="tcp:170053:8"/>concerne not us) doe ſtrangly affect the hearers, and do raiſe ſtrong paſſions and affections in them with a deſire to imitate what they repreſent well done; and a compaſſion for the misfortunes and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that arrive undeſervedly to worthy and well natured perſons. How efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then muſt the conſideration of Chriſts paſſion and ſufferings be to beget like, and farre ſtronger ſentiments in any man that ſhall inſiſte upon them? The dignity of the perſon; the extremity of his baſe and cruel uſage; his great deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, even from them that ſo treated him; his undergoing all this, meerly for our ſakes, and particularly for every one of us; and the infailable certainty that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of all theſe paſſages are undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, would move a heart of ſtone that ſhould entertain it ſelf leiſurely with theſe thoughts.</p>
            <p>And ſuch compaſſion and tenderneſſe for his ſufferings to redeem and deliver us from miſery, will beget love and paſſion in us to his perſon. And hee being God, as well as man; our affections that thus begun
<pb facs="tcp:170053:9"/>divinity, which is the period of all ſpirituall exerciſes, and the top of all perfection, in this life; and the happineſſe of the next. And therefore our Saviour told his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and loving penitent, that the ſhare ſhe had choſen ſhould never bee taken from her.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe grounds <hi>Albert</hi> recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the continuall meditation of Chriſts paſſion, to be alwayes joyned with the other exerciſe of depuring our imaginations, and hearts from the images and affections of all created objects whatſoever; Making thereby a ladder of his humanity to climbe up to his divinity; which if we ſhould look upon it without that veyle between us and it, would ſtrike us blind. As when a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal ſimple is too ſtrong for our ſtomack to bear ſingly in its own ſubſtance, phyſitians uſe to allay and weaken it with ſome gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle liquor that is agreeable to our taſte: and then drinking what delighteth us, with pleaſure we ſwallow health.</p>
            <p>But Madam, I perceive I engage my ſelfe before I am aware in a talk, I am not able to go through with. Nor is it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:170053:9"/>for this little treatiſe (of as great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, as it is of little bulk) requireth neither commentary nor apologie. My ſending it to your Ladyſhip is an action of duty, and of affection. The firſt, in giving you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the expence of my time in this place, where I have bin now a just week; and intitling you to all I ſhall ever do, or bring to paſſe, in any kind whatſoever du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my whole life: And the other, in communicating to you what hath afforded me ſo much contentment, and may prove ſo ſolidly beneficial to me, if it pleaſe God to give me grace to make right uſe of it. I beſeech your Ladyſhip pray him ſo to do, and to be pleaſed to give me your bleſſing. <hi>Calis</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of October (the feaſt of the glorious Patriarke of the Carthuſians, who moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably practiſed and instituted, what this treatiſe recommendeth) in the year <hi>1649.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Sonne, K. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170053:10"/>
            <head>To my Lady <hi>Winter,</hi> the wife of Sr. <hi>John Winter,</hi> late of Liddne in the County of Gloceſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worthy Author giving me the view of this Tranſlation in <hi>Paris,</hi> at my comming from thence I begged a cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, which he was pleaſed to beſtow: and as he performed the work for his private uſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, and after dedicated it to his vertuous Mother the Lady <hi>Digby:</hi> So I, who have no other ſhare then the conveying it to be printed for the publique good, do offer up my little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie therein to your La: Yet not for this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but that indeed I willingly take occaſion to tell the world, how much my Lady <hi>Winter</hi> is eſteemed and valued by her faithfull Friend, and Kinſman,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>and moſt humble ſervant, W: Gr:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170053:10"/>
                  <head>A TREATISE OF Adhering to God.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the utmoſt and higheſt perfection that it is poſsiblefor a man to arrive unto in this life.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have been caſting with my ſelfe, how I might frame for my owne uſe, a compleat &amp; perfect draught (as far forth as our nature is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of in this lifes baniſhment and peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) of what is the higheſt and nobleſt action for a man to employ himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. And ſurely this is none other, then a ready, vigorous, conſtant and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate adheſion unto God Almighty; by a totall abſtraction (as much as is poſſible) from all creatures whatſoever. For, the end of Chriſtian perfection is Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; by which a Soule cleaveth to her Creatour. And unto this adheſion of Charity, every man in particular is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably obliged under paine of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170053:11"/>Heaven, ſo far forth as concerneth the obeying Gods commands, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelfe to his Divine will: which obedience ſhutteth out whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is repugnant to the eſſence and habit of Charity; and conſequently all mortall ſinnes. But religious perſons have a further obligation then this, by having bound themſelves to Evangelicall perfection, and to ſuch duties, as though they be but of counſill and ſuperogation, yet by them the way is made more ready, and more ſecure to bring the obſervers of them to their journeys end; which is the poſſeſſion, and fruition of God. And the obſervance of theſe ſhutteth out not only what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Charity; but alſo all other obſtacles that may in any wiſe hinder or looſe the fervour and activity of Charity, or that may retard or ſlacken the ſoules union with God Almighty, which is in a great meaſure performed, by an intire and efficacious abrenunciation of all creatures whatſoever; even of our owne ſelves.</p>
                     <p>Now ſeeing that <hi>God is a ſpirit,</hi> and that <hi>he ought to be adored in Spirit and in truth; Joh.</hi> 4. (that is to ſay, by knowledge and love, by underſtanding and affection voide of all mixture with any corporeal ſpecies,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170053:11"/>or materiall imaginations) hence it is that we are thus taught in the Goſpel; <hi>when thou ſhalt pray, enter into thy chamber,</hi> that is, into the inner roome of thy heart) <hi>and ſhutting the doore, Mat.</hi> 6. to wit, of thy ſenſes, there with a pure heart, a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and a firme faith, <hi>pray to thy father</hi> in ſpirit and in truth <hi>in ſecret.</hi> All which is done, when a man laying aſide all other affaires and thoughts, withdraweth himſelfe wholy into himſelf: &amp; then ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, and forgetting all created objects whatſoever, the ſuperiour part of his ſoule onely powreth out before Jeſus Chriſt her deſires to her Lord God, in deepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and with confident ſecurity; and in ſo doing, dilateth, diffuſeth, drowneth, inflameth and reſolveth herſelf into him, through the violence of love with the whole weight of her heart, and with the utmoſt ſtraining of all her faculties and powers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II. <hi>How one may cleave and intend wholy to Chriſt, deſpiſing all other things.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BUt he who deſireth, and is reſolved to apply himſelfe to ſuch a ſtate, muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170053:12"/>lay downe for an abſolutely neceſſary ground, that he muſt ſhut his eyes and all his ſenſes to all manner of outward impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and affaires that may cauſe any trouble, and muſt caſt from him all cares &amp; ſollicitudes, as being altogether uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in any creature whatſoever, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looking upon them as hurtfull and pernicious to him. And then he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire his whole life into himſelfe; and there have no other object to entertaine his thoughts withall, but Jeſus Chriſt woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and crucified. And that with a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall attention, and with all earneſtneſſe and ſtraining himſelf to his utmoſt power, he muſt make it his onely buſineſſe, to paſſe by him into him, that is to ſay, by his Manhood into his Godhead, by the wounds of his humanity, into his glory and Divinity: and there readily and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely commit himſelfe and all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth him, to his unwearied, and al-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing providence; according to St <hi>Peters</hi> expreſſion, when he ſaith (<hi>caſting all your care and ſolicitude upon him,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. who ruleth and diſpoſeth all things: And to St <hi>Paul,</hi> when he biddeth us <hi>bee ſolicitous for nothing, Phil.</hi> 4. And to that direction of the Pſalme, which adviſeth us <hi>to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170053:12"/>all our thoughts upon the Lord, and he will nouriſh us. Pſal.</hi> 54. And to the ſenſe of the other which ſaith, <hi>It is good for me to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to God Pſal.</hi> 74. And alſo of the other that telleth us, how the Royall Prophet <hi>kept the Lord alwaies before his eyes, Pſal.</hi> 15. And like the Soule in the Canticles that rejoyceth <hi>for having found him whom her ſoule loved. Cant.</hi> 3. The end wherof will be, <hi>that all goods will come along in company with that ſupreame good.</hi> And this is that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hidden treaſure, and that pearle of ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable value which ought to be preferr'd before all other goods whatſoever, and is to be ſought with ſtrength of Spirit, and purchaſed with humble confidence, with tranquillity of mind, with carefull guard upon ones tongue, with indefatigable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and even with the loſſe of all outward conveniences, and of ones very honour and reputation. For otherwiſe what would it availe a religious man to gaine the whole world, if at the ſame time he ſhould ſuffer detriment in his ſoule? or what profiteth him the ſtate he hath enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelfe in, the holineſſe of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; the habit of perfection that hee hath put on; and the whole oeconomy of his outward converſation, unleſſe he bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170053:13"/>enlivened with the Spirit of Humility, and truth, where Chriſt dwelleth by faith, that is informed and quickned with charity? To him that is in this condition it may be truely ſaid, <hi>the kingdome of God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you;</hi> which is our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>In what the perfect conformity of man with God conſiſteth in this life.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is moſt certaine, that by how much more a mans Soule is buſied and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about inferiour and humane affaires, by ſo much the further ſhe is carried away from ſuperiour and heavenly conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in which conſiſteth the flower and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of devotion. And by how much more intenſely and fervently ones thoughts are recollected from remembring, loving and conſidering of inferior objects, and are fixed upon ſuperior ones, by ſo much their proper will bee the perfecter, and their contemplation the purer. For it is impoſſible that ones attention ſhould at the ſame time be entirely and perfectly knit upon two diſtinct objects, that are as farre diſtant from one another, as light and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170053:13"/>darkneſſe are. He that adhereth to God, dwelleth in light: but he that is glewed to the world is overwhelmed with darkneſſe. And therfore the ſublimer perfection of a man in this life, is to be ſo united to God, that his whole ſoule withall her powers and facultyes bee in ſuch ſort wound up and riveted in him; and that he remember nothing but God; and that all his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being united in a joyfull exerciſe of love, doe repoſe ſweetly in the ſole fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Creator. For, the image of God expreſſed in the Soule, conſiſteth in theſe three faculties of hers: namely in the underſtanding, the memory, and the will. And as long as they in any man are not entirely impreſſed with the ſtamp of God, and the whole extent of them are not taken up with that, his ſoule cannot bee ſaid to bee Deiformed, or perfectly reſembling the divinity, according to the ſtate in which the firſt ſoule was created. For, God is the forme of the ſoule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe ought to be impreſſed, as waxe is with a ſeale, and ſhe ought to have ſuch a relation to him, as the coppy of a picture hath to its originall. But this is never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly done, but when ones reaſon and underſtanding is perfectly illuminated
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170053:14"/>(according to its capacity with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, who is the ſupreme veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and his will is perfectly ſet on fire with the love of him who is the ſupreme good; and his memory is totally abſorbed in contemplating and rejoycing in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happineſſe, and in repoſing ſweetly and delightfully in that thought. Now ſeeing that the glory of heavenly bliſſe conſiſteth in the full poſſeſsion of theſe three, which will be compleated in the next life, it is evident that a perfect beginning of them is the utmoſt perfection that our preſent life is capable of.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>How our operations ought to be in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall part of our Soule onely, and not in our Senſes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HE therefore is happy, who by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all receiving and expunging of all ſpecies and Images from his fantaſie, and by reducing and turning his conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inwards, and there raiſing his Soule up to God, groweth at length to that paſs, that he forgetteth all materiall imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and hath no other entertainment for his thoughts within him, but to imploy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170053:14"/>them continually by pure and ſimple operations of underſtanding and love, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the only pure and ſimple object ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated above all compoſition, or materia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; which is none other but God. Be ſure then that you baniſh out of your mind all imaginations, pictures, and formes of all things whatſoever, that are not God; to the end that your whole excerciſe and imployment within you, be immediatly concerning God, and be performed ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by your underſtanding, and by your will and affections. For the end of all ſpirituall exerciſes is the applying all ones thoughts to God, the buſying them ſingly about him, the attending to him onely, and the repoſing entirely in him without any other ſollicitude or occupation of the mind; and this, fingly in the intellectuall part of our ſoule, by pure underſtanding, and by vehement ſtraine of love, without any admixture of Corporeall imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And this exerciſe is of ſo refined and pure a nature, that the fleſhly organs of the body cannot reach unto it; but it is performed by that part of us which mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to be men, and reaſonable creatures; that is by our underſtanding and our will. And therefore as long as a man entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170053:15"/>himſelfe with his ſenſes, and with the picture and impreſſions that outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects doe make in any of them, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth upon them; It may rightly be ſaid of him, that he hath not yet growne out the motions and limites of his brutall nature; that is, out of the low orbe in which he partaketh with brute beaſts, and is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them. For they have cognition, and are wrought upon by ſuch materiall and ſenſitive ſpecies; and have not in them any ſpring of a higher ſtraine. Whereas man in regard of his reaſonable ſoule, that is endowed with the powers of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of loving, and of the free will, is created according to the image &amp; likenes of God: and by them he ought to receive into his ſoule pure and immediate im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſons from God himſelfe,, and cleave firmly to him, and become one with him. And therefore the divell through his envy to mankind is moſt vigilant and active to hinder a man from that exerciſe as much as he can; as being a kind of eſſay and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in this life of the eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he ſhall injoy in the next. And in purſuance of that deſigne he laboureth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with his utmoſt power to draw our minds from almighty God, ſometimes by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170053:15"/>one temptation, ſometimes by another, ſometimes raiſing paſſions in us, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles begetting in our minds needleſſe ſollicitouſneſſe, ſuperfluous cares, and indiſcreet anxieties; otherwhiles diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering us with unquietneſſe within our ſelves, or with diſsolute converſation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, or with unreaſonable curioſity of what concerneth us not; ſometimes with begetting in us an itch to read Books of unprofitable Subtilties, or to diſcourſe of what belongeth not to us, or to inquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter newes &amp; occurrences of the world; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles by aſſaulting us with adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and contradictions, &amp; with an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of ſtratagems that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployeth againſt us: whereof though many may ſeeme to be but of ſmall moment, and not to be accounted as ſins, yet in very truth they are exceeding great hinderanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of this holy and ſublime exerciſe. And therfore, be they concerning great affaires, or concerning but ſmall ones; nay, though they may ſeem to be advantageous to us, or even neceſſary to be attended; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they ought to be wholly cut off and caſt away, and our ſences ought to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced from them. And accordingly, whatſoever we happen to heare, or to ſee,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170053:16"/>or whatſoever in any ſort chanceth to paſſe before us, we muſt have a ſingular care that we tranſmit it not from our outward ſenſes to our fantaſy, and there frame an image or repreſentation of it, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our thoughts with it. Which if we be diligent in, and do keep ſuch images from reſiding in our memory, and from recurring to our thoughts; they will be of no impediment unto us, nor cauſe us any diſtraction whiles we are praying, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating, ſinging Pſalmes, or about any other ſpirituall exerciſe; nor will ever after returne to moleſt us againe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon any occaſion of what important affairs ſoever that may occurre unto you, let your ſecurity &amp; fortreſſe be to keep it out from admittance into your thoughts, and from making any impreſſion upon your mind; and to caſt it and your ſelfe readily and confidently and entirely, with peace and ſilence and calmneſſe, into the arms of Gods all knowing and all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing providence; and then he will fight for you; and will certainly deliver you from all the evills that might arrive unto you from that coaſt; and will ſhine in your ſoule by Divine conſolations. Whereas if you ſhould thinke to overcome the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170053:16"/>that will ariſe againſt you, by your owne induſtry and vigilancy, and by taking them to taske, and wreſtling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in your owne thoughts; all that you will gaine by wearying your ſelf out with continuall ſollicitude, and with having your reſtleſſe imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons day and night fixed upon what you would prevent or compaſſe; will be to diſcover plainly in the concluſion, that all humane wiſdome is meer folly, and that the reſult of ſuch toyleſome enſlaving of the ſoule to vaine and unreaſonable occupations, is but loſſe of time, abaſing of our mind, and even a fretting out of the ſpirits that give life to our body; without effecting what we have ſo earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly and paſſionately laboured for. When therefore any accident happeneth to you of what kind ſoever it commeth, make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is ſent you by a tender Father that is continually watchfull over you, and accordingly receive it with an even and unmoved mind, and let it not afford you matter either for diſcourſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or for thoughtfullneſſe within you. But uncloath your imagination from all ideas and images of corporeall objects, according to the duty of your condition
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170053:17"/>and profeſſion; that ſo you may cleave faſt with a pure ſoule to him you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed your ſelfe, and that no created thing whatſoever may intervene betweene you and him, and that through the ſacred wounds of his humanity, you may be ſecurely and ſteadily wafted over to the incomprehenſible light of his divinity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the purity of heart, which above all things is to be aymed at.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF therefore you deſire to walke in the ſtraight and direct way that will bring you readily and ſafely to your journeys end, both of grace in this life, and of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the next, you muſt with a conſtant and never interrupted attention, employ all the diligence and induſtry you are able to purchaſe a perpetuall cleaneneſſe of heart and purity of mind, and untroubled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſenſes. You muſt recollect as it were into one burning point all the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and affections of your Soule, and caſt it upon God, and fixe it irremove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably upon him. Which to doe efficaciouſly you muſt withdraw your ſelfe from the converſation of your friends, and indeed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170053:17"/>of all mankind (as much as is poſſible for you) and from all buſineſſe of what kind ſoever that may in any ſort divert or retard this deſigne of yours, laying hold of all conveniences that may beget a quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and tranquillity in your ſoule, and may advance your contemplation: beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your ſelfe for that purpoſe to the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and ſolitude of ſome cloſe retreate, where you may lye ſecure at anchor, free from the Rocks and dangers of this fading life (againſt which ſo many doe ſuffer unhappy ſhipwrack) and be ſheltered from the noiſefull ſtormes of the deceitfull world. But while you are in this haven you muſt not grow remiſſe, as though now all dangers were paſt, and your worke were at an end; but you muſt ſee your ſelfe with a continuall vigilancy to keepe your outward ſenſes ſtrongly ſhut, and to watch narrowly your owne hart; ſo as no enemy may breake in upon it, and cauſe in it any diſquiet, or taint the purity of it with the droſſie images of ſenſible and terrene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. This purity of heart is the top of all ſpirituall exerciſes, and is the end for which he that aſpireth at Evangelicall perfection, forſaketh the world; and is the compenſation that in this life he can have
<pb facs="tcp:170053:18"/>of all his labours. And therefore you muſt ſtrive with all earneſtneſſe to free your heart, and to ſequeſter your ſenſes and affections from all objects whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that may hinder the liberty of your ſpirit, or that may have any power to draw or inveigle, or bind you to them. And you muſt ſumme up all the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your ſoule, and recollect all the diſperſions of your heart, and fixe them inſeparably upon that true and ſupreame good, which being but one, and in it ſelfe moſt ſimple, containeth all good in it. And by ſuch cloſe adheſion to God, and dereliction of all created objects, and rejecting of all terrene and fraile affections, you muſt endeavour to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your heart through Jeſus Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a kind of divine nature; and when once you come to thrive ſo happily in this high imployment, of unclothing and purifying your imagination from all ſpecies and images reſiding in it, and of refining and exalting your heart to ſuch a ſimplicity that it can reſt no where but in God, and that you now begin to ſuck in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bowels of your ſoule pure ſtreames from the fountaine of his divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and that you reliſh them ſavourly,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170053:18"/>and that you unite your ſelfe to him by conforming your ſelf in every thing to his divine will; then this alone, this ſingle exerciſe is all that you need buſie your ſelf about. This will ſuffice for your whole occupation. In this will be ſummed up all your other ſtudies; your reading and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating of the holy ſcriptures, your lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of god and of your neighbour. And in a word, this will bring you to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of perfection that this life is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, by ſuch wayes and paths as no man is able to delineate, but are purely the work of the holy Ghoſt within you, and of his unction. Let therefore all your ſtudy, endeavour, and labour be to reduce your heart unto ſuch a ſimplicity, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unmoveable at the ſtrokes of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward objects upon your fantaſie, you may repoſe your underſtanding, and ſettle your affections with ſuch tranquillity, and fixedneſſe in God, within your ſelfe, as if your ſoule were already arrived to that happy ſtate of unvariable Eternity, in which the preſent fruition of the all-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending divinity ſo overreacheth all times and actions, that there is nothing either paſt or to come in relation to it; and therefore can admit no change or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viciſſitude
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170053:19"/>of accidents. And this is attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by forſaking and abandoning your ſelfe entirely without any reſtriction, for the love of Jeſus Chriſt; and caſting your ſelfe upon God with a pure heart, and a firme confidence in his all-ſeeing provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and reſigning your ſelfe with an unmoved patience and ſecurity in all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents and tribulations to his Fatherly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of you. But this cannot be effected, unleſſe you turne continually inwards, and there treat cloſely with your owne heart, without ever wandring aſtray out of it, and that you deliver your ſelfe (as far as it is poſſible) from all outward impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and that you keep the eye of your ſoule in a perpetuall purity and tranquillity, and that you preſerve your underſtanding from all commerce with the formes and images of inferior and tranſitory things; and that you weane the affections of your will from all terrene and fading goods, and ſettle them with the whole activity of your ſoule upon the only true ſupreame good; and that you raiſe and fixe your memory upon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall repreſentation of that eſſentiall and uncreated good; and that thus your ſoule, with all the powers and faculties
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170053:19"/>of it, abſorbed up in God Almighty, doe become one ſpirit with him, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on all hands to be the higheſt perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that in this life mans nature is capable of. For by this union of ſpirit and love with God; and by ſuch conformity, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tranſformation of your will to Gods eternall wil; you become by grace, ſuch as God is by nature. And you may lay up this for an infayleable truth, that in the very inſtant wherein a man is enabled by Gods aſſiſtance to overcome his own will, by caſting from him all inordinate love and ſollicitude, and by delivering himſelf totally in all his neceſſities into Gods hands, to diſpoſe and ſteer his courſe as he pleaſeth; he by this becommeth ſo accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God almighty, that he preſently repleniſheth him with his grace, by which is kindled ſuch a fire of charity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection in his ſoule, as immediatly expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all ambiguity and feare, and faſtneth his hope and confidence in God. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly no condition can be ſo happy, as to rely ſecurely on all occaſions upon him, who we are ſure hath no defect in his nature. Therefore if at any time you find a wavering in your owne thoughts, or an inclination to any ſollicitude for ought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170053:20"/>that may have happened unto you, throw your ſelfe with a careleſſe ſecurity into his armes; and he will imbrace you, and cure your feares, and will deliver you from the aſſaults, and from all danger of it. Beleive it, thoſe points if you duly rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and digeſt them within your owne heart; will more conduce to make your life happy, then if you abounded with all the riches, delights, honours, wiſdome and knowledge that this deceitfull world can beſtow upon her favourites; &amp; that in them you exceeded all the men that have ever lived.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That true devotion conſiſteth in adhering to God by the Vnderſtanding, and Will, depured from all commerce with materiall Objects.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Seeing then by how much the more you ſhall cleanſe your thoughts from the droſſy images of created objects, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter your ſelf from outward, wordly and ſenſible occupations; by ſo much the more your ſoule will recover her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vigour, and relliſh of thoſe objects that are of kinne to her; The beſt leſſon you can learne, is to keep her from all commerce with the ideas and images of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170053:20"/>corporeall things. For certainely there is nothing ſo pleaſing to God, as a mind in ſuch a ſtate: And when he findeth ſuch a one, who being free from all carnall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, paſſions, and diſtractions, attendeth unto him onely, and with a pure under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding fixeth ſingly upon him; then he maketh good what he hath ſaid of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that it <hi>is his delight to be with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men.</hi> Whereas if you ſuffer your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to lodge the ſpecies of ſenſible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in her ſtore-houſe, or allow your thoughts and imagination to entertaine themſelves with ſuch, it is impoſſible but that your ſoul ſhould be tincted, either with the relicks of what you have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converſed with, or with the impreſſions of what you are preſently buſy about. And then you may be ſure the holy Ghoſt (who withdraweth himſelf from thoſe thoughts that are without underſtanding) will make himſelf a ſtranger unto you. Therefore he who loveth Jeſus Chriſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ought to be ſo united by a pure under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, &amp; by a good will to the goodneſs, &amp; to the wil of god, and ſo abſtracted from all wordly conſiderations, and ſo void of all paſſions, that he heed not what opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons other perſons do entertaine of him;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170053:21"/>whether he be beloved, or hated; eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or derided; or what any man can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt or effect againſt him. For, it is the goodneſs of the Will that ſupplyeth for all things, and is above all things. And therefore as long as a man is owner of a good Will, and is purely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, and united to God in his Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; he is out of danger of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any prejudice by his fleſh, or ſenſuall part, or by his outward man, though it ſhould be inclined to evill, and be reſty and benummed to good; nay though his inward man ſhould be dry and heavy in the exerciſe of devotion, he is ſafe, as long as he cleaveth firmely to god by faith, and by good will in the ſuperiour part of his ſoul. And this he doth, when he reflecteth upon his own imperfection, &amp; nothingneſs; and frameth a ſtrong and deep judgement, that all his good conſiſteth in his creator onely, and with all the powers and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his ſoul renounceth himſelfe, and all creatures, and drowneth himſelf and all his powers in his creator, in ſuch ſort that he directs all his operations purely and entirely to him, and neither ſeeketh, nor deſireth any thing but him, in whom he already perceiveth that all good, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170053:21"/>al perfect felicity is compriſed. And by thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he is in a manner transformed into God: ſo that he can neither think, nor underſtand, nor love, nor remember any thing but God, and of God: and if he chanceth at any time to ſee either himſelfe, or any creature, he ſeeth them not as they are in themſelves, but onely as they are in God. Nor doth any ſhare of his love reſt in them, but all of it paſſeth through them to God, and reſteth in him. And this knowledge of truth alwaies rendreth a ſoul truely humble, and maketh it ſevere to it ſelfe, without ever judging others; whereas worldly wiſedome ſwelleth a ſoule with pride, vanity, and empty winde. Take this then for the foundation of all ſpirituall doctrine; that if you deſire to arrive to the true knowledge, ſervice, familiarity, and full poſſeſſion of God Almighty; you muſt neceſſarily deveſt your heart of all ſenſible love, not onely of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, but of all creatures whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; that ſo you may with a pure and entire heart, and with all the powers of your ſoule, apply your ſelfe, freely, without all double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, care and ſolicitude to your Creatour, caſting your ſelfe in all occaſions with a full confidence upon his ſingle providence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170053:22"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>In what manner ones heart is to be recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected within ones ſelfe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is very truely ſaid in the book of the Spirit and the Soule, <hi>Cap.</hi> 21. that to aſcend up to God, is to enter into ones ſelfe. For without all doubt, he, who turning his operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inwards, pierceth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> through himſelfe, and goeth beyond himſelfe, is really and truely raiſed up to God. Wee muſt therefore have a care to recollect our heart from the diſperſions, and diſtractions of this world, and to recall it to thoſe joyes it will find within it ſelfe; that ſo it may in time be enabled to keepe it ſelfe ſteady in the light of divine contemplation. For the life and reſt of our heart conſiſteth in fixing it by earneſt deſires upon the love of God, and in taſting the ſweetneſſe of thoſe conſolations, which with a liberall hand hee giveth to thoſe who love him. And the reaſon is obvious why we are ſo frequently fruſtrated of the experimentall enjoying of this happines, and are not able to taſt and ſavour it in the full ſweetneſſe of it. For whiles our ſoule effuſeth it ſelfe upon exterior objects, and is choaked with the ſollicitude of tranſitory things, ſhee entreth not into her ſelfe, by the ſetting before her eyes thoſe ſolid conſiderations which her
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170053:22"/>memory ought alwaies to be ſtored withall; whilſt ſhe is peſtered and overclouded with the images of creatures, ſhe returneth not into her ſelfe by the ſuperiour part of her underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, into which no ſuch object can have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance; and whiles ſhee is intangl'd with concupiſcences, ſhe is hindred from reverting into her ſelf by vehement deſires of that interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or ſweetneſſe, and ſpirituall joy, which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely to a purified and enflamed ſoule: &amp; ſo lying groaning among theſe preſent ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, and fading objects, ſhe is not able to turne her ſelfe inwards, and diſcerne the image of God that is formed there. It is therefore abſolutely neceſſary for him who aymeth at this noble and high pitch, that with profound humility, and yet withall with entire confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he raiſe himſelfe above himſelfe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the whole machine of creared beings, by the abnegation of them all; ſaying thus to himſelfe; he whom my heart hath choſen from among all things, whom it ſeeketh above all things, and whom it loveth and deſireth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all things, is not to be knowne by my ſenſes, nor compriſed by my imagination; but is above all that is Senſible, &amp; above all that is Intelligble: he is not perceptible to any faculty of mine, but yet he is ſuch, as I may deſire, and love him with all the powers and faculties of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170053:23"/>my ſoule: he is not repreſentable by any ſhape, yet I may thirſt after him with the moſt enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med affections that can be raiſed within mee: nor can he be priſed, or valued neere his worth, by all I can ſay or thinke of him; and yet my heart, if it be cleane from all droſſie affections, can ſeiſe upon him, and unite it ſelfe to him by exceſſes of love. For he is beautifull, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, infinitely beyond all things in the world, &amp; is of infinite goodneſſe &amp; perfection. And then after ſuch like diſcourſes and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, his ſoule entereth yet deeper into it ſelfe, and raiſeth it ſelfe yet higher above it ſelfe, and looſeth it ſelfe (as I may ſay) in the divine miſt of incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble light. And this manner of aſcending even to the aenigmaticall beholding of the moſt holy Trinity, in Jeſus Chriſt, is by ſo much the more enflamed and vehement, by how much thoſe operations, which carry the ſoule upwards, are more interiour; and is by ſo much the more profitable, &amp; raiſeth one ſo much higher, as the love one ſoareth with is more vigorous and fervent. For in ſpirituall operations the meaſure of their height and excellency is their interiourneſſe, and recollectedneſſe from all outward diſſipation. Therefore you muſt not give over, or ſit you down to reſt, till you have gotten ſome taſt, as it were an earneſt-penny of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170053:23"/>that fulneſſe which will hereafter ſwell you up; and till you have obtained ſome firſt fruits of that heavenly ſweetneſſe which will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pleaſe beyond all meaſure the ſpirituall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of your ſoule: nor muſt you ſlacken your pace in running after that divine odour you begin to have the wind of, till you come to ſee the God of Gods in Sion. For you muſt ſettle this as a fundamentall rule in the progreſſion of the ſoule, and in the adheſion and union to God within you, that you muſt never retire nor repoſe, till you have obtained what you ayme at. Conſider thoſe who travell up a mountaine; and apply to your caſe what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth unto them. If a ſoule engulfe her ſelfe by concupiſcence among thoſe things that ſlide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long beneath her, ſhe preſently loſeth her way in a labyrinth of infinite diſtractions, and of oblique and crooked waies, and is as it were divided from her ſelfe, and is torne into as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peeces, as there are ſeverall objects that ſhe is glewed unto by her deſires. And from hence proceedeth the inſtability of mens actions, without any fixedneſſe upon the reſolutions they had once taken; their toylſome running, without arriving to the end of the courſe, and their perpetuall labour without any reſt. But if a ſoule doe raiſe her ſelfe by divine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and love, from what is beneath her,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170053:24"/>and would entangle her in a multitude of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions; and, forſaking all creatures without her, do recollect her ſelfe within her ſelfe unto that one, immutable, all-ſufficient good, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhe will find the image within her ſelfe; and doe learne to dwell and converſe alwaies with it; and doe cleave inſeparably to it, by enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med deſires and affections; ſuch a one will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe daily in ſtrength and perfection, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to the knowledge and deſire that lifteth her up to that one ſupreame, immutable good; Till ſhe herſelfe become at the laſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable too; and arrive without feare of change, to that true life, which is none other but God himſelfe; where without all ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or variety of actions, &amp; without all viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of time, ſhe may repoſe eternally in that interior quiet, and ſecret manſion of the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; unto which the contemplation of Jeſus Chriſt will bring her, who is the way that all they muſt travaile in, who propoſe heaven for their journeies end; and is the truth of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and the life of the Soule.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170053:24"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>How, in all chances, a ſpirituall man ought to reſigne himſelfe to God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Conceive, that by what is hitherto ſaid, you now diſcerne how the more you cleanſe your imagination from the ideas of all outward things, and ſequeſter your ſelfe from all wordly and created objects, and unite your ſelfe to God by your Will and Vnderſtanding, ſo much the more you approach to the ſtate of innocency &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And what condition can be better, happier, or more delightfull then that? ſtrive then to keep your mind free from all impreſſions that may amuſe or intangle it: and let not your thoughts have any commerce with the world, or even with your freinds; nor be you concerned in the proſperities, or adverſities, either of them, or of your ſelfe; nor buſie your mind with any worldly affaire whatſoever, either paſt, preſent, or to come: Nay, not ſo much as to be over ſollicitous of your owne paſt ſinnes: but with a kind of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſimplicity, and purity of heart, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine your ſelfe to be out of the world, ſingly with God almighty; as though your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170053:25"/>ſoule were already in the ſtate of Eternity, ſever'd from your body. Which if ſhe really were, it is certaine ſhe would then no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er trouble her ſelf with ſecular affaires, nor care what poſture the world were in, nor be concerned with peace or warre; or faire weather or foule, or any other ſecular oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current whatſoever; but would attend wholly, &amp; uniformedly to God alone, and would reſt in him, and cleave inſeparably to him. Begin from this very houre, in ſome ſort, to doe thus. Sever your ſelfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven now, by your affections, from your owne body. Baniſh from your thoughts all created things whatſoever, either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, paſt, or to come; and fixe the purified eye of your ſoule, as ſteadily, and as earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as you can, upon the eternal, increated light. And when you are throughly clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from all corporeal images, &amp; your ſoul is delivered from all worldly incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and miſts, you will become like an Angell that were aſſigned to a body, but received no prejudice in his operations by that ſociety, nor were annoyed with vaine and ungovern'd thoughts. Let your ſpirit therefore ſtrengthen it ſelfe againſt all manner of temptations, trouble, and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; that in all fortunes it may remaine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170053:25"/>unmovable in God. And when any diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, or tediouſneſſe, or opreſſion of mind ſhall grow upon you, be not for that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, or out of hart, or betake your ſelfe to vocall prayers, or to outward conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but attend onely to raiſe your ſelfe up to God by pure acts of your will, and of your underſtanding, and to adhere to him in the ſuperior part of your ſoule, whither your corporeall part will or no. For a ſoule that is truly devout, ought to be ſo united with God, and to conforme her will ſo entirely to his that ſhe have no relation or adheſion to any creature, no more then if her ſelfe were not yet created; or as though there were nothing elſe in being, but God and ſhe. And ſuch a one will receive all things with indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, from the hand of divine providence; and reſigne her ſelfe uniformely in all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to God, with patience, tranquillity, and ſilence. When therefore you ſhall have arrived to this ſtate, no creature will then interpoſe it ſelfe between God and you. And this is that, which by the profeſſion of religion we aime at. For by the vow of voluntary Poverty, we deprive our ſelves for the whole durance of our life of all outward goods: by the vow of Chaſtity we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170053:26"/>renounce our bodyes; and by the vow of Obedience, we forſake our wills, and even our ſoules themſelves: ſo that after theſe, nothing remaineth that may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene between god and us, to keep us at a diſtance from one another. This we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our ſelves unto, when we enter into religion, &amp; cloth our ſelves with the habit of our order. But whether or no our inward purity do anſwer to our outward profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that reſteth between God and our own conſciences. But certainely we ſhould degenerate exceedingly, and ſin grievouſly againſt God, and againſt his Juſtice, if we ſhould do otherwiſe, and ſhould preferre the creature before our Creatour; and by our affections, and deſires, cleave rather to that, then to him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>That the contemplation of God is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before all other exerciſes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Now becauſe all things that are not God, are but works of his hand, &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects proceeding from him their Creator, &amp; that their powers &amp; beings are limited, and, as being produced of nothing, are allwayes tending to nothing; it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170053:26"/>that whiles they exiſt, there cannot paſſe a moment wherein they draw not their beings, their conſervations, their working, and all elſe that followeth of their beings, from God their Creatour who is the fountain &amp; well-head of all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: in respect of whom they are not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lame and defective, but even as nothing is to that which is Being it ſelf, and as that which is finite and narrowly circumſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, is to what is infinite. And therefore in him onely, and about him, and for him, let us employ all our whole life: admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his infinite Wiſedome, his infinite power, and other his infinite perfections, who is able with one act of his will to create if he pleaſe infinite new worlds, each of them infinitely more perfect then this which he hath created. Without doubt no contemplation of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, nor fruition of love by means of the affections is ſo profitable, ſo perfect, and ſo bliſsfull, as that which hath direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for its object God almighty our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and true ſupreme good, from whom all things doe flow, in whom all things are contained; by whom all things are preſerved, and for whom all things were made; who is infinitely all-ſufficient both
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170053:27"/>to himſelf, and to all things elſe: who containeth in himſelf from all eternity the perfections of all things whatſoever, reſumed in ſo pure a ſimplicity, that he hath no mixture in him, nor hath any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident belonging to him, but all that is in him, is he himſelf: with whom, and by whom, all the cauſes of fleeting and decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things have a permanent ſtability: in whom reſide the immutable originalls of whatſoever is ſubject to change and viciſſitude: and in whoſe eſſence do live the eternall principles and modells of all creatures whatſoever, either reaſonable or unreaſonable, or any wayes depending of time: who completeth all things: who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely filleth all things, and every thing, eſſentially with himſelfe; who is more inward, and more preſent to every thing, then the thing is to it ſelfe: and laſtly, in whom all things are ſummed up and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited together, and do live eternally. But if any perſon ſhould through weakneſſe of capacity, or want of trayning to theſe conſiderations, find them of too hard di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion for him; and be inclined to ground his immediate contemplation rather upon the creatures, then upon the creator: yet let him have a care to order his medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170053:27"/>or contemplation in ſuch ſort, as out of it may riſe in him a delectation in God one and threefold; and in his breſt may be kindled the fire of divine love, and of true life, which may light and guide him to eternall felicity. And herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the difference between the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of faithfull Chriſtians, and that of the heathen Philoſophers. For theſe latter directed their contemplation to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and therefore it reſteth in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; the bettering of which was the end &amp; ſcope of their meditation. But chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians doe imploy themſelves in this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, for the love of him whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template; that is, of God, who is the object of their contemplation. And therefore it reſteth not finally in their underſtanding by cognition; but paſſeth to their will by love and affections. For it is much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for a man to know Jeſus Chriſt, and be united to him ſpiritually by grace and Charity; then without them, to have him in them corporally, or even eſſentially. Now the ready meanes to enlarge the eye of contemplation, is, to have ones ſoule abſtracted from all creatures, and to keep it reflected upon it ſelfe; whereby it mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a ladder of it ſelfe, by which it aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170053:28"/>to the contemplation of God himſelfe. And when it is fixed, there it burneth with deſire of heavenly, eternall, and divine goods; and looketh upon all tranſitory ones at a huge diſtance, conſidering them indeed as nothing. But of the different methodes of contemplating God, that which proceedeth by negations, is the more excellent &amp; ſublime. In which we begin by denying all corporeall things of him, or whatſoever may be graſped by our ſenſes, or figured by our imagination. Then we proceed by denying of him, all intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible objects, or whatſoever may be fad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domed by our underſtanding. And laſtly, we deny even Being it ſelfe of him, in that ſenſe, and under that notion, as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Beings of creatures. And then we are arrived (according to <hi>Dionyſius Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagita</hi>) to the higheſt pitch of union with God, that our nature is capable of in this life. And this is the miſt which God is ſaid to inhabit; Into which <hi>Moyſes</hi> entered; and by it come to unacceſſible light. But in this journey we muſt advance by order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſteps, the animal part muſt precede the ſpirituall. And therefore we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the labour of action, before we can attaine to the reſt of contemplation;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170053:28"/>and we muſt lay a foundation of morall vertues, before we can aſcend to the top of ſpeculative ones. All which when thou haſt ſeriouſly conſidered (my ſoule) tell me if it were not folly and madneſſe to buſie thy ſelfe in vaine about multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of things? Doſt thou not ſee how thou art ſtill in want, &amp; in neceſſity, as long as thou entertaineſt thy ſelfe with them? Give over then all other imployments and thoughts; and ſettle thy ſelfe to this onely one of contemplating, and loving the one onely true good, in which all good is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, and thou needeſt no more. Oh! how unhappy were that man who knowing all things elſe, and enjoying all things elſe, were in the mean time ignorant of him? And though he ſhould know all things, together with him; yet they would adde nothing to his happineſſe: for that conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſingly in him. And therefore the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt ſaith, <hi>The knowing of thee is eternall life: Jo.</hi> 17. And the Prophet, <hi>I ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated when thy glory appeareth. Pſ.</hi> 16.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170053:29"/>
                     <head>CHAP. X. <hi>That actuall and ſenſible devotion is not ſo much to be regarded, as to adhere to God with ones will.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BUt when I ſo much inculcate the rayſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of affections, and love in the ſoule, my intention is not to adviſe you to inſiſt upon actuall devotion, or upon ſuch ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſweetneſſe (oftentimes accompanyed with teares) which the ſpirituall exerciſes of tender and devout perſons are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanyed with. I mean only that you be mentally united to God by your will in the ſuperior part, and intellectuall, of your ſoule. For no devotion whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, or ſpirituall exerciſe is of ſo high and excellent a ſtraine, or ſo pleaſing to God, as to keep our mind free from the images, likeneſſe, and Ideas of creatures. And this is that which particularly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to a religious man, and which his profeſſion obligeth him unto. For as by his vow he hath renounced all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whatſoever; ſo in his practiſe he ought to keep his mind free from them, to the end he may have his thoughts and affections continually fixed and riveted
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170053:29"/>upon God alone. And therefore be careful to renounce your selfe in all things; that ſo having reduced your ſelfe into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect nakedneſſe of all creatures, you may follow Chriſt our Lord God and Saviour, and tread in thoſe ſteppes he hath marked out unto us, who was truly poore, chaſt, and obedient; and was humbled lower then ever man was: many were ſcandaliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as appeareth in the Goſpell) becauſe their weak eyes, not being capable of that divine light that ſhone in all his actions, they rejected and were offended at what was too ſublime for them. Now to give you an inſtance of the abſtraction I require in you from all created things, whereby you may conceive what it is I recommend unto you in all the reſt; I pray you conſider what Sentiments a ſeparated ſoule hath of her body ſhe hath left behind her. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe regardeth not what becometh of it, nor is ſhe concerned whither it be burned or hanged, or any wayes contumeliouſly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; nor hath ſhe any regret for any inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ill treatments or ſcornes that may be heaped upon it. But ſhe hath all her powers &amp; attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fixed upon that ſtate of Eternity ſhe then enjoyeth, and upon that one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle neceſſary thing that our Saviour hath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170053:30"/>recommended in the Goſpell. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10. Such ſentiments as theſe I would have you beget in your mind, even in this life, whilſt your ſoule is in your body. Regard it no more, then if your ſoule were parted from it, and let all your thinking be of that one neceſſary point: and reſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, you will here find a wonderfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace and ſwift progreſſe in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining true purity of mind, and ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of heart. For that one neceſſary thing will immediately follow of it ſelfe, upon your baniſhing all images from your thoughts, and upon your withdrawing your ſelfe from all implications, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from created objects; and you ſhall then immediately find God ſhining in your ſoule, and you will feele her cloſely united to him, that nothing can ſever her from him. Neither will any allurements inveigle her, nor any torments force her from her beloved. You will be invincible in all tentations and aſſaults; as the holy Martyrs and Fathers were, and the reſt of the elect, and all thoſe that are now Saints in heaven: who deſpiſing all created things, attended to no other thought but ſuch as concerned ſecurity and eternity of the ſoule in God. And thus armed within,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170053:30"/>and united to God by the affections of their will, they overlooked and neglected all the things of this world, as though their ſoule were quite out of it, by having taken leave of their body. Thus you ſee the admirable power that a rightly placed love, and a will united to God hath, rven ſo much, as though through the impreſſion that a ſoule receiveth then from God, and through her ſpirituall ſeparation from her compartner the fleſh, ſhe looketh upon her outward man at a far diſtance, and as if he belonged not to her, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglecteth all the violences that can be uſed to her fleſh, as though they were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon an other, or upon ſome crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that were not a man. For he who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereth to God, becometh one ſpirit with him: and conſequently in reſpect of that of him by which he adhereth to God, he ceaſeth in ſome ſort to be himſelfe, or what he was before. Of which tranſforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the fleſhly part not being capable, but remaining ſtill in its owne groſſie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is as it were divorced from the ſoule, that hath taken too high a flight for her fleſh to follow her in; and therefore ſhe looketh downe upon it as if it concerned her not. Be ſure therefore never to give
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170053:31"/>admittance within you to any thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of God: but remember that your happineſſe and perfection dependeth on raiſing up your ſoule to him; and on having him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies preſent to the eye of your underſtanding; and on fixing it ſo attentively upon him, that it looke upon nothing beſide, as though there were nothing in the world but God and your ſelfe. And in this union you will enjoy thoſe happy embraces, that are in this life a faire beginning of the bleſſedneſſe and joyes of the next.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>In what manner we are to reſiſt temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to beare tribulations.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere is no man who commeth to God with a true and entire hart, but he is tryed with ſundry vexations and temptations; in which I can give you this comfort, that though you be troubled by feeling them, yet you will receive no prejudice by them, as long as you yeeld no conſent unto them, but beare them with humility, patience, and equality of mind. And if you ſhould be aſſaulted with temptations of blaſphemy, oruncleane repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; the beſt you can doe in that caſe is to neglect them, and account them as nothing.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170053:31"/>For be they in themſelves never ſo foule, or wicked, or horrid; yet as long as they go no further than your fantaſie, and range there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your will, they are not to be imputed to you, nor doe they require that you ſhould trouble your conſcience with them. The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my will certainely fly, and leave you in peace, if you contemne him and his attempts. For he is proud, and cannot endure to be neglected and ſcorned. And therefore your beſt remedy is to regard them no more, then as if they were but flyes buzzing before your face againſt your will. And conſider how unſeemly it were for the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt to be made to looſe ſight of his maſter, by the importunity of a contemptible flye, and fall into indignation, murmuring and complaints at ſo triviall a matter, as a ſlight temptation of ſuſpicion (for example) a ſadneſſe, or detraction, or inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, or any other ſuch ſmall adverſity; all which (like flyes chaced away with the mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ones hand) are put to flight by an act of the will elevated up to God, and by love ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in him. For ſuch a will bringeth a man to be the particular poſſeſſion of God (who will have a care of what is particularly his owne) and to have the Angels his guardians and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectours. And therefore is peace promiſed to men of good will. Neither can any thing of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170053:32"/>greater value be offered to God, then a good will. For ſuch a one is the origine of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ſoule, and the mother of all vertues. And whoſoever hath it, hath compleately all that is requiſite for him to be happy. And therefore if any obſtacle happen to hinder the good which ſuch a will deſireth, God ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and giveth the recompence, as if the effects had ſucceeded to his deſire: whereupon by an immutable decree he hath entayled merit and demerit upon the will: according to which he proportioneth our reward in heaven, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in hell. And the merit of the will is nothing elſe but love: that is, a great earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſerve God; a ſweet affection in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, and a moſt fervent deſire of enjoying God. But to conclude the ſubject of this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: let this truſt comfort you in all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that to be tempted is no ſin, but an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for you to exerciſe vertue, and a Schoole to profit exceedingly in. And indeed, the whole life of man is but a temptation upon earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of the love of God, and of the great power it hath.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALl that we have hitherto ſaid, and in a word, whatſoever is neceſſary for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170053:32"/>is performed beſt, moſt compendiouſly, moſt ſecurely, and moſt effectually, by love; which alone, is able to ſupply for the want of any thing requiſite to bring a man to beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; and in it, is contained the plenitude of all good; for by it the object upon which one exerciſeth it with earneſtneſſe, becommeth preſent to one. It is love onely that turneth us towards God, that transformeth us into God, that we adhere to God by, that uniteth us to God, and maketh us become one ſpirit with him; and laſtly, that rendereth us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in this life by grace from him, and in the next life by glory in him. For, love reſteth not, but in the fruition of the object beloved, and in a plenary and peacefull poſſeſſion of it. It is the way by which God deſcendeth to mankind, and by which man aſcendeth up to God. For where Charity (that is to ſay, where love) is not, God can have no reſidence. If therefore we have Charity, we have God: for God is Charity. Nothing hath a keener edge then love; nothing is more ſubtile, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſearcheth farther, nor pierceth deeper. It alloweth it ſelfe no repoſe, untill it hath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed all the qualities and dimenſions of what it loveth, and have dived into the very center of it. It will cleave ſo faſt to the beloved object, that it will become one with it, or rather it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170053:33"/>will not be content, till it have ſo transformed it ſelfe thereinto, as it ceaſeth to be any longer it ſelf, by becomming (If ſo I may ſay) the very thing that it loveth; and that it admitteth no immediate thing whatſoever to remaine, or intervene between it, and what it tendeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which is God himſelfe. Unto whom it tendeth with ſo great a vehemence and force, that it is in a perpetuall unquietneſs and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, untill it have run through all things that lye between them, and have ſeiſed upon him, and have ſubmerſed it ſelfe in him. For love hath an unitive and transformative power, that changeth the lover into what hee loveth, and againe the beloved into the lover: ſo that each of them is in the other as intrinſecally as poſſibly can be. Which how it is, will the more plainely appeare, if we conſider ſeverally the commerce that is between them in the two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall powers of the ſoule, the underſtanding &amp; the will of him that loveth. Firſt, in regard of the underſtanding, and apprehenſive faculties; the beloved is in the lover by his continuall forming the image of the beloved in his thoughts; where hee converſeth intimately with him in a moſt ſweet and delightfull manner; and againe the lover is in the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not contenting himſelfe with a ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all knowledge of what belongeth to him, but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170053:33"/>uſing his utmoſt indeavours, to dive into the inmoſt ſecrets of him, and to reach the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. Secondly, in regard of the will, and of the affective &amp; deſiring faculties, the beloved is ſaid to be in the lover by reſiding in his heart through an affectuous compleaſance, and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous delectation in him: and the lover is in the beloved by having the ſame deſires which he hath; by willing the ſame things which hee willeth; by diſliking the ſame things which he diſliketh, by rejoycing and grieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the ſame, and by having an exact con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity with him in all things, as though hee were not a diſtinct perſon from him, but even he himſelfe. For love draweth the lover out of himſelfe, and planteth him in the beloved, and ſetleth him moſt intimately there: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is ſaid in the <hi>Canticles, Cant.</hi> 8. that love is as ſtrong as death, which carrieth the ſoule out of the body. And it may well be ſaid, that the ſoule is more where it loveth then where it liveth. For ſhe is in the beloved according to her owne nature, and as ſhe hath an exiſtence belonging to her ſelfe, that is, by her will &amp; underſtanding; whereas her giving life to a body is an action of much lower de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and onely as ſhe is the forme and part of a whole; in which conſideration ſhe hath no prerogative above the formes of bruit
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170053:34"/>beaſts. We may therefore conclude, that to draw us from outward and ſenſible objects into our ſelves, and from thence to carry us to our ſaviour Jeſus Chriſt; and in him to unite us to his divinity; there is no other way, no other meanes then the love of him, and the ardent deſire of his ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that through his humanity we may feele, and perceive, and taſt the preſence of his divinity. So great is the power of love, that it is able to raiſe the ſoule from the earth to the higheſt heaven. Nor is it poſſible for any perſon to arrive to Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but by the wings of love and deſire. Love is the life of the ſoule, her wedding garment, and her perfection: In which is compriſed the Law and the Prophets, and the whole doctrine of our Saviour. And therefore the Apoſtle ſaith to the Romans, that love is the fulneſſe of the law: <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. and to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that charity is the end of all that is comanded. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170053:34"/>
                     <head>CHAP. <hi>XIII.</hi> Of the quality and utility of prayer: and how ones heart is to be recollected within it ſelfe.</head>
                     <p>BUt ſithence, we are not able of our ſelves, either to love, or to doe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good worke, nor can of our owne ſtocke offer any thing to God (from whom alone floweth all that is good) that is not already his: the only thing which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for us to doe, is, that according to the inſtructions which he hath vouchſafed to give us by his owne divine mouth and bleſſed example, we have recourſe to him by prayer in all our occurrences; and that we proſtrate our ſelves before him, like poore needy beggers, like wretched miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able bondſlaves, like feeble deſolate chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and ſo with deep groanes lay open our hearts before him, repreſenting our diſtreſſed condition with all ingenuity &amp; ſincerity, with feare and ſhame; yet ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with confidence and love; and beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with the utmoſt vehemence and fervour of our ſoule, to protect and aſſiſt us in our imminent dangers; and in the cloſe admitting and abandoning ourſelves en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely and ſecurely into his hands, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170053:35"/>reſerving any thing at all to our ſelves; but acknowledging whatſoever we have, or are, to be abſolutely his. And then, that will be fulfilled in us, which the holy abbot <hi>Iſack</hi> (ſpeaking of his manner of prayer) ſaith in the following words:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Caſſian. Collect.</hi> 10. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</note> Then we ſhall be one in God, and our Lord, and only he will be all in all to us; when that perfect love of his with which he loved us firſt, ſhall likewiſe on our ſide have paſſed and bee converted into the affection of our heart. Which will be when all our love, all our deſire, all our ſtudy, all our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, all that we ſhall think, imagine, ſpeak and hope will be God alone; and that a like unity as is between the father and the ſonne, and againe betweene the ſonne and the father, ſhall be transfuſed into our ſoule and mind: that as he lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us, with a ſincere, pure, and indiſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable charity, ſo we may be joyned alſo to him by a perpetuall and inſeparable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection; whereby thus linked unto him, all that we ſhall deſire and hope for, that we ſhall underſtand, that we ſhall ſpeake of, and that we ſhall direct our prayers unto, may be God only. This therefore ought to be the intention, the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170053:35"/>ayme, and the end of a ſpirituall man, that he may come to poſſeſſe herein his corruptible body, an image of the next lifes beatitude; and that he may begin in this world, to receive a kind of earneſt penny, and taſt ſome drops of that beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, converſation, and glory, which we ſhall have in heaven. This I ſay is the end of all perfection; that our ſoule being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified from all carnall droſſe; it may day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be refined and ſublimed up to ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all objects, untill our converſation, and all the motions and affections of our heart do become one continued prayer. And when our ſoule, free from all earthly alloy,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Caſſ. Col.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> ſhall thus breath and pant after God onely (on whom alone the intention of a ſpirituall man ought to be fixed, and ſo ſuch an one, the leaſt ſeparation from him will ſeem a preſent and cruel death,) and ſhall be in a manner ſent beforehand to him, by injoying ſo high a calme from all carnall paſſions (which might inveigle and draw it to their objects) that it may firmly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſolubly adhere to that one ſupreame good; then the direction of the Apoſtle will be fulfilled, who biddeth us pray without intermiſſion; 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. and in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170053:36"/>place, lifting up pure hands eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where without anger and contention. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. For where the operation of the mind is abſorbed (if ſo I may ſay) with ſuch purity, and is transformed from a terrene and groſſe nature, to a ſpirituall and Angelicall ſhape; then whatſoever ſhe ſhall receive into her ſelfe, whatſoever ſhe ſhall employ her ſelf about; and whatſoever ſhe ſhall doe, will be a moſt pure and a moſt ſincere prayer. To conclude, if you ſhall continue, without interruption, that courſe I have traced from the beginning of this diſcourſe, it will be as eaſie and ready for you in your introverſion and recollection, to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate and to injoy God, as in nature it is to live.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>That in all judgments, we ought to reſort to the witneſſe of our conſcience.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is of no ſmall availe, for attaining ſpirituall perfection, and the purity and tranquillity of the ſoule in God; that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoever ſhall be ſpoken, thought or done concerning us, we preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre in ſilence to the inward ſecret of our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170053:36"/>heart and mind; and there ſequeſtred from all other objects, and wholly recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected within our ſelves, we call our ſelves to a ſtrict account, for diſcovery of the bare truth of what we make our inquiry about. And there we ſhall find that it will be no advantage for us, but rather much prejudice, to be praiſed and honoured from without, if in the mean time our heart within us reproacheth us of faulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and guilt. And as it profiteth one nothing to be praiſed by men, whiles his owne conſcience accuſeth him: ſo on the other ſide, he is never the worſe for being contemned, reproached, and perſecuted, whiles in the tribunall of his owne heart he findeth himſelfe innocent and irrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible: Or rather, upon ſuch occaſions, he hath reaſon to rejoyce in our Lord with patience, ſilence, and tranquillity. For no adverſity can hurt him in whom iniquity raigneth not. And ſince it is a certain truth, that as no evill remaineth unpuniſhed, ſo no good paſſeth without reward; let us beware of expecting or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ours like hypocrits, from men: but referr that wholly and ſoly to God, to give it us, not in this life, but in Eternity that laſteth for ever. It is then evident,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170053:37"/>that no action we can doe, can be nobler or better, then alwaies, in all our tribulations, and accidents whatſoever, to reſort into the ſecret of our owne ſoule; and there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, our helper in our temptations and tribulations; and humble our ſelves through acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our owne ſinfulneſſe; and praiſe God our Father, that correcteth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth when he judgeth fit. And let us be ſure to receive all things, either concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves or others, proſperous or adverſe, with equanimity, and with a ready and confident reſignation of our ſelves into the hand of his infallible and Fatherly providence. And by doeing thus, we ſhall obtaine the remiſſion of our ſinns, the delivering us from all bitterneſſe, the contemning of ſweetneſſe and ſecurity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, the infuſion of grace and mercy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, the ſetling and ſtrengthening us in the familiarity of God, our ſucking abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant conſolations from him, and our firme adheſion and union with him. Let us therefore beware of imitating thoſe, who through hypocriſie, and after a Phariſaicall manner, do ſtrive to appear better, and otherwiſe then they are; and do labour to give men a better conceit of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170053:37"/>themſelves then in their owne hearts they know they deſerve; and do hunt after out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward humane prayſe and glory, whiles their ſoules within are full of impotent paſſions and deſires, and grievous ſinns. Certainly whoſoever ſhall ſeek after ſuch vanities, which is the extremity of folly and madneſſe, the reall good we have formerly mentioned will fly from him; and reproach and ſhame will in the end betide him. Keep therefore continually before thine eyes the bad that is in thee, and thy unaptneſſe to all good. Know thy ſelf aright, that thou mayeſt be humbled. And conſidering thy great ſinns, and the exceſſive evills that are in thee, repine not at being eſteemed the moſt unworthy, vile, and abject creature in the world: but repute thy ſelfe among other men, like droſſe mingled with gold, like darnel growing among wheat, like chaffe ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with corn, like a wolfe among ſheep, and like ſatan among the children of God; and ſhunn all honour or preference from others, fly with all might and maine from the infection of this peſtilence, from the poyſon of praiſe, and from the vanity of oſtentation; leaſt according to the royall Prophet, the ſinner be praiſed in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170053:38"/>the deſires of his owne ſoule. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9. For according to the other, They who ſpeake thee bleſſed, doe deceive thee, and doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the way of thy ſtepps. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 3. And our Saviour threateneth us with woe, when men ſhall bleſſe us, and ſpeake well of us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>How the contempt of ones ſelfe may be cauſed in a man, and how profitable that is.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is moſt certaine that the better a man is acquainted with his owne unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and baſeneſſe, and the deeper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit he frameth thereof; the further and the clearer he looketh into the Majeſty of God; and the meaner a man appeareth in his owne eyes through the valew he putteth upon God, upon truth, and upon juſtice; the more worthy and pretious he is in the eyes of God. Let us therefore continually buſy our thoughts upon thoſe conſiderations that may beget in us a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of our ſelves, and a beliefe that we are unworthy of receiving any good turne. Let us mortifie and diſpleaſe our ſelves, and ſeeke to pleaſe God onely. And let us be content to be reputed (as we are) moſt unworthy and vile wretches.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170053:38"/>When any tribulations, afflictions, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries do come upon us, let us not be mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at them, nor entertaine any unquiet thoughts, or indignation, or animoſity againſt thoſe that bring them upon us: but with meekneſſe and gentleneſſe of ſpirit, let us conclude within our ſelves, that we deſerve all the injuries, ſcornes and miſchiefs, with abandonments that can arrive unto us. For certainly he who is truly penitent, and whoſe heart is full of compunctions, abhorreth being honoured and loved by men, and is content to be hated, deſpiſed, and trodden upon, to the very laſt; that ſo he may attaine to true humility, and to a ſincere, firme adheſion unto God alone, with a pure heart. Which adheſion to God onely, and loving of him onely, together with the hating of our ſelves, and thinking worſe of ones ſelfe then of all creatures elſe, and the deeming himſelfe deſpiſable, and deſiring to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and ſcorned by all men elſe, requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no outward labour, or ſtrength of body; but rather, the ſolitude and retirement of the body, whilſt the heart laboureth by affections, and the mind is quiet from all worldly affaires: to the end that ſetting your heart upon the right object, and ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170053:39"/>the diſtracting multiplicity of creatures out of our mind, and ritiring our ſenſes from all converſation with mean intertainments; our ſoule may then raiſe it ſelfe up to a familiarity with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and divine things, whiles our body is ſequeſtred by ſolitude from earthly ones. By doeing thus, we ſhall change our ſelves after a ſort into God. To attaine unto the perfection of this State, we muſt be alwaies upon our guard to paſſe no judgement or cenſure upon our neighbour, much leſſe to contemne or deſpiſe him. And we muſt hartily deſire to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all men as the droſſe of the earth, and the reproach of human nature, and to be abhorred by them like dirt and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe, rather then to abound with any delights whatſoever, or to be honoured or advanced by men, or to enjoy any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall ſatiſfaction, or tranſitory conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. And we muſt wiſh for no more of the advantages, or continuance of this life, then meerly what is neceſſary for us to bewaile and lament without intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our tranſgreſſions and ſinns, and to grow up dayly in the diſeſtimation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, hatred, and annihilation of our ſelves in our owne eyes; that ſo we may
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170053:39"/>become more pleaſing in Gods. And laſtly we muſt have no regard or ſollicitude for any thing in the world beſides God alone, but ſettle all our love and affections upon him, and cleave inſeparably to him, and have no object in our hearts, but our lord and ſaviour Jeſus Chriſt; by whoſe power all things ſubſiſt, and by whoſe providence all things are governed. The conſolations of this life are the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enemies, that can be encountered with to hinder one in ſuch a happy courſe. Remember then that this is not a place for you to receive delights or contentments in; but to weep and lament in from the bottome of your heart. If then your ſoule be ſo dry that you cannot weep, the very conſideration of that, will afford you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant matter of teares. But if you doe weep, you will have reaſon to increaſe your lamentation, by conſidering that through your grievous offences and ſinns, you have drawn upon your own head this dolefull cauſe of ſorrow; which whiles it lyeth ſo heavy upon you, what madneſſe were it in you to let your thoughts range aſtray after any other affaìre that you are not concerned in? The delinquent at the barre, that ſtandeth there pleading for his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170053:40"/>life, and feareth the ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, from a ſevere judge, little regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what is done abroad in the market place, or how the ſheriffe marſhalleth and diſpoſeth his guards for the ſecurity of the priſoners. So he that hath conſidered rightly the condition that his ſoule is in; and upon that conſideration entertaineth ſuch a deep ſorrow as belongeth to him; will have no reliſh of any of the delights of this world, nor will his heart afford any roome for anger, vain-glory, indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any other paſſion whatſoever to harbour in it. And if at any time you chance to caſt your eyes upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented and cheerfull ſtate of other happy perſons, that ſwimme in the delights of pure love, which baniſheth all ſorrow; do not preſently flatter your ſelfe that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth alſo to you, who are compoſed of like parts as they, to have a manſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. For as there are priſons and dungeons for malefactors, whiles the well diſpoſed citizens live at eaſe in their owne houſes; ſo there are different exerciſes and formes of living for thoſe whoſe paſt ſinns oblige them to penance and mourning, &amp; for thoſe that have preſerved themſelves with greater purity and innocence. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170053:40"/>theſe latter would have no advantage of the former; and injuſtice would have more freedome then innocence. We may then conclude, that we muſt abandon all creatures; wee muſt deſpiſe them all; and wee muſt repudiate and fly from all the delights of this world; that ſo with entire faith, wee may lay a ſolid foundation of repentance and mourning. And if once we attaine to love Jeſus Chriſt in truth, and to ſigh after him from the bottome of our hearts, and to beare him continually there, &amp; to conform all our actions to the example hee hath given us; and to have a real griefe for our ſinns, and to have a lively apprehenſion of the next world, &amp; to have the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the laſt judgement, and of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall torments of hell, all waies before our eyes; and to be continually apprehenſive and ſollicitous of the ſtate we ſhall be in when we leave this world; we ſhall then moſt aſſuredly be delivered from all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to created things, and be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with nothing that is of a fleeting and tranſitory nature: and we ſhall arrive to ſuch an impaſſibillity, as not onely to be contented with preſſures and encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon us, and with injuries done us;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170053:41"/>but even to be afflicted, and ſo think that day loſt wherein we receive not ſome ſcorne, or malediction, or ill intreatment for Gods ſake. The perfection of which impaſſibillity conſiſteth, in being free from all vices and paſſions, and in having a pure and cleane heart; and in having our ſoule adorned and repleniſhed with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. Which to attaine unto, it will much availe us, to beleive our ſelves already out of the world; and ſince we are ſure that one day we muſt neceſſarily dye; let us make account we are already dead. But becauſe through the frailty of our nature, and the cunning and malice of our enemy (who endeavoreth to ſlide into our beſt actions, and ſo corrupt them) theſe inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and abſtracted exerciſes may be lyable to miſcarriage, as all humane actions are, let this bee the touchſtone to try all our thoughts, words, and deeds by; whether they be according to God or no: namely, whether we become more humble, more diſaffected with the world, more recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected within our ſelves, and more atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and ſtrong in the purſuite of God. For if we ſhould find it otherwiſe with us, we might with reaſon ſuſpect that what we did, were not according to God;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170053:41"/>nor pleaſing to him, nor profitable to our ſelves.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>How the Providence of God extendeth it felfe to all things.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NOw to the end that according to what we have have hitherto diſcourſed, we may without any diſturbance, readily, ſecurely, and calmely be raiſed up to God Almighty, and bee immediately joyned and united to him, and cleave inſeparably to him with a perfect quietneſſe, evenneſſe, and untroubled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind, aſwell in adverſity as in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, in death as in life: wee muſt reſigne our ſelves entirely, and commit all things confidently to his never erring, and never ſhaken providence. In doing which we can have no difficulty or reluctance, when we call to minde how it is he, and onely he who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth unto all creatures their being what they are, who endoweth them with their individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vertues, powers and faculties; who ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them to work and performe all the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that their nature can reach unto; and who doth ſo wonderfully order and range their infinite variety with exact proportion of number, weight and meaſure, that like a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of ſo many parts, they compoſe the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170053:42"/>harmony and beauty of the created world. If you conſider the plants of nature, you will finde them ſeated between two un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding agents; the one giving them their eſſentiall being, the other working in them ſuch modifications, and changes, as may bee introduced into them by art. This latter is the ſhare of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam;</hi> who how ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable ſoever they be in the rare productions of their Dedalean witts; yet they muſt ſit ſtill, and their Art muſt remaine buried in them, if bounteous nature did not furniſh them with materialls and ſubjects to worke upon. In the ſame manner Nature her ſelf would fall to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, were it not for a continuall emanation of being into every individuall plant of hers, from him that is the author of all being. For as art preſuppoſeth the productions of Nature, without which ſhee cannot exerciſe her skill; ſo the individualls of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doe preſuppoſe the operation of God almighty; creating, conſerving, ordering, and governing them; without which they would preſently run into confuſion, &amp; into their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall nothing. And in the whole courſe of them, &amp; in the oeconomy of them we may reade his infinite power, wiſedome, goodneſſe, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall mercy, juſtice, truth, charity, and unchangeable eternity, and immenſity. For
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170053:42"/>nothing can ſubſiſt and work by its owne vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power; it oweth that entirely to God, and to him onely, as being the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the originall principall, and the Cauſe of all action in every agent whatſoever. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth immediately for every thing, &amp; cutteth out their ſhares, even to the leaſt &amp; inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableſt creature he hath made. From the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt, none of them eſcapeth his providence, or ſwarveth from the line he hath traced out to them; whether it be in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of nature, or in theirs that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of voluntary and free agents, or in theirs that ſeeme to be hatched out of the caſuall concurrence of ſeverall cauſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any precedent deſigne, in thoſe that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly produce them. This all-ſeeing and all-governing eye of Gods providence, reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not onely to all that is in nature, but even to all that God himſelfe can doe. For ſince he can doe nothing but according to the rules of wiſdome, and that a wiſe agent diſpoſeth all things that are in his power, by order and foreſight; it is neceſſary that all he doth, muſt fall under the order of his providence. So that it extendeth to all things, and to all actions, even to the recluſeſt thoughts of mans heart. Therefore Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170053:43"/>reaſon to adviſe us, to abandon ourſelves wholly to his all-ſufficient provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; without having any anxiety for what may befall us, when he ſaith, that we ought to caſt all our ſollicitude upon him, for that he hath care of us. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. As also the royall Prophet in theſe words: Pitch your thoughts upon the Lord, and he will feed you. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 54. And the like you will find in <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> in theſe words. Look about you children of men, and know that no man ever hoped, and was confounded, nor remained under his commandements, and was forſaken by him. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2. And our Lord himſelfe warneth us that we be not ſollicitous, ſaying what ſhall we eat? <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt there is no bleſſing ſo great, that we can hope for at Gods hands, but we ſhall receive it of his liberality and mercy; if we rely on him with due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, according to his promiſe: in the <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> what place ſoever your foot ſhall tread upon ſhall be yours, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11. For the meaſure of a mans receiving, ſhall be the largneſſe of his heart in deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his poſſeſſion ſhall reach as far as he hath reached out the foot of his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; which hath moved Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170053:43"/>ſay, <hi>God the creator and diſpoſer of all things aboundeth with the bowels of ſo great mercy, that how great favour and grace ſoever wee can raiſe our confidence to begge of him, ſo great we ſhall certainly receive at his hands.</hi> And therefore our ſaviour biddeth us in S. <hi>Marke,</hi> that <hi>whatſoever we aske for in our prayers, we ſhould believe that it will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us; and the effect will enſue accordingly.</hi> And moſt certainly, the more ſtrong, and the more preſſing that our confidence ſhall be in God; and the more violent aſſault it ſhall give him, with humility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, the more ſecurely, the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, and the more ſpeedily wee ſhall impetrate and obtain what wee hoped for. The great impediment of ſuch noble confidence; that keepeth it down from ſoaring to this high and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pitch, is the wieght of ſinne: Where that aboundeth, a ſoul is laſy and benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and unable to raiſe it ſelfe up with confidence to God. For redreſſe of this miſchiefe, let him whoſe heart is in earneſt turned from the world, and converted to God, conſider the infinite power of God Almighty. Let him remember how all things are poſſible to him: and what his Will once determineth, muſt of neceſſity
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170053:44"/>be crowned with its effect; and that what he gainſayeth, hath an impoſſibility of ever coming to paſſe. And therefore it is as eaſy to him, if he pleaſeth to remitt and cancell an innumerable multitude of ſins, be they never ſo enormous, as to forgive one ſingle one. And from the leaſt ſingle one a ſinner is not of himſelfe able to riſe, and deliver himſelfe, no more then from the greateſt load of innumerable ones. For of our ſelves, we are not able ſo much as to think, much leſſe to do any good thing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. All that is of that nature, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from God onely; who worketh it in us: and to him onely we muſt referre, and acknowledge it. Therefore our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from ſinne belonging not to our ſelves upon our own ſcore, but being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely the work of God Almighty his power and mercy; and all things being alike eaſie to him; wee may with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence commit our ſelves into his fatherly armes, and promiſe our ſelves from him a plenary abolition of all our miſdemean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, be they never ſo many and never ſo great. Yet let us beware that a wrong ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, or a miſtaking of this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, draw us not into preſumption, or into a fooliſh ſecurity. For it is alſo moſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170053:44"/>certain, that looking upon the condition as the caſe ſtandeth on his part, it is farre more dangerous for him to be involved in many ſinnes, then to be under the weight of one only ſinne. For it is an inevitable decree, that no evil action can eſcape un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed; and to every mortal ſinne an infinite puniſhment is due. If this were not, Gods Juſtice would ſuffer thereby: ſince every ſuch ſinne is an injury in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect line done to God himſelfe; who is of infinite Dignity, Honour and Reverence. But this is ſo evident a truth, that I need put no more weight on this ſide the ſcale. Whoſoever ſhall look upon his own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthyneſs, is out of danger of falling into preſumption. He is in greater, of being kept back by puſillanimity, from thoſe bleſſings that by a vertuous confidence hee may obtain. Therefore for his comfort and advantage, let us adde to what wee have already ſayd, how God (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle telleth us) hath a certain and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible knowledge, and keepeth an exact account of thoſe who are his: and that it is impoſſible for any of theſe to miſcarry. They will be preſerved ſecure in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of all difficulties, dangers, ſcandals, ſchiſmes, perſecutions, quarrels, haereſies,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170053:45"/>tribulations, adverſities, and temptations whatſoever. For God hath foreſeen from all eternity the number of his elect; and the laſt act of their lives, that ſettleth them in the ſtate of merit; And nothing can change or ſhake his infallible previſion. All things cooperate to their good, as well the bad as the good, adverſity as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, as well what is without them, as what is within them, and dependeth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately of themſelves: with onely this difference, peradventure, that out of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity they come more refined and ſhine brighter. Let us therefore ſecurely and readily commit our ſelves, and all things elſe to the divine providence; who when it permitteth evill, it is with a deſigne to draw good out of it. And conſequently it is good that ſuch evils ſhould be, and that God ſhould permit them. Nor can they be otherwiſe, or more, then ſtrictly what he alloweth. For his knowledge fadom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the extent of all things; his power maſtereth and limiteth them as he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and his will diſpoſeth and turneth them to good. For as all that is good proceedeth from his immediate operation; ſo thoſe evils that are permitted by him,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170053:45"/>are turned into good by his goodneſſe and power. Out of which we may gather his omnipotency, his infinite wiſdome, his clemency through Jeſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and repayrer, his mercy and juſtice, the efficacy of grace, and the diſability of nature, together with the beauty of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, reſulting out of the comparing and harmony of contrarieties; the chiefe of which are the vertue and reward of the good, and the wickedneſſe and puniſhment of the bad. Nor can wee look upon the courſe and oeconomy of Gods converting and ſaving of a ſinner, but with exceeding great comfort and joy. On the ſinners part, the change of his heart, his contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for having offended God, his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his ſinnes, and his doing penance for them: On Gods ſide, his admirable meekneſſe, his mercy, his charity, and his infinite goodneſſe, are ſubjects for a man to meditate continually upon, and to praiſe God everlaſtingly for. But let him not grow too bold upon Gods mercies, for his delivering a ſinner by ſuch admirable and ſecret pathes from the miſery he was enfoulded in; For ſuch grace is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to all offenders: but the greateſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170053:46"/>number by farre periſheth (alas) in their dangerous and crooked wayes; and as they are deprived of grace in this life, ſo are they baniſhed from glory in the next, and condemned to eternal puniſhment and torment. From which Jeſus Chriſt of his mercy preſerve us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170053:46"/>
                  <p>A CONFERENCE With a Lady about choyce of <hi>RELIGION.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Herring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> at the Anchor in the New-Exchange. 1654.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="conference">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170053:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170053:47"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y being conſcious to myſelf how confuſedly and intricately I have delivered my conceptions unto your Ladyſhip, upon the ſeverall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of diſcourſe we have had together, concerning that important ſubject of what faith and religion is the true one to bring us to eternall happineſſe (wherein your Ladyſhip is ſo wiſely and worthily inquiſitive and ſollicitous) hath begotten this following writing; in the which I will, as nere as I can, ſumme up the heads of thoſe conſiderations I have ſometimes diſcuſſed unto you in converſation. And I will briefly and barely lay them before you, without any long enlargement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; as having a better opinion of the reflections that your Ladyſhips great underſtanding and ſtrong reaſoning ſoule will by your ſelfe make upon the naked object ſincerely propoſed, then of any commentary I can frame upon it. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſuch diſcourſes as theſe are deeper lookt into, when they are pondered by a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170053:48"/>prudentiall judgement, then when they are examined by ſcientificall ſpeculations.</p>
                  <p>But with your leave, I ſhall take the matter a little higher then where the chiefe difficulty ſeemeth to be, at which your Ladyſhip ſticketh; conceiving that if we begin at the root, and proceed on ſteppe by ſteppe, we ſhall find our ſearch the eaſier, and the ſecurer, and our aſcent to the concluſions we ſhall collect, will be the more firme and vigorous.</p>
                  <p>We will therefore begin with conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing why faith and religion is needfull to a man, before we determine the meanes how to find out the right faith: for that being once ſetled in the underſtanding, we ſhall preſently without further diſpute reject what religion ſoever is but propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that hath not thoſe proprieties which are required to bring that to paſſe, that Religion in its owne nature aymeth at. And this muſt be done by taking a ſurvey of ſome of the operations of a human ſoul, and of the impreſſions made in it by the objects it is converſant withall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Your Ladyſhipp may be pleaſed then to conſider in the firſt place, That it is by nature ingrafted in the ſoules of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to deſire beatitude, (By which word
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170053:48"/>I meane an entire, perfect, and ſecure frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſuch objects as one hath vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment affections unto, without mixture of any thing one hath averſion from.) For the ſoule having a perpetuall activity in it, muſt neceſſarily have ſomething to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it ſelfe about: And according to the two chiefe powers of it (which are the Vnderſtanding &amp; the Will) it employeth it ſelfe, firſt in the ſearch and inveſtigation of what is true and good; and then, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the judgment it maketh of it, the Wil followeth, and with affections graſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at it, which if it happen to ſeaze upon, the ſoule is at content and at reſt; but if it miſſe, it is unquiet, &amp; laboureth with all vehemence to compas it: and if any thing happen that is repugnant to the nature of it, it uſeth all induſtry and efficacious meanes to overcome and baniſh it: ſo that all the actions and motions of it, tend to gaine contentment and beatitude.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the next place you may pleaſe to conſider, that this full beatitude which the ſoule thirſteth after, cannot be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this life. For it is apparent, that intellectuall goods, as ſcience, contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and fruition of ſpirituall objects and contentments, in their owne nature
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170053:49"/>are the chiefe goods of the ſoul, and affect her much more ſtrongly and violently then corporal and ſenſual ones can doe: for they are more agreeable to her nature, and therefore move her more efficaciouſly when they are duely reliſhed. But ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall goods cannot be perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and injoyed, as long as the ſoul is immerſed in the body, by reaſon that the ſenſuall appetite maketh continual warre againſt the rational part of the ſoul; and in moſt men maſtereth it, and in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt, this earthly habitation doth ſo draw down and clogge, and benumme the noble inhabitant of it (which would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies buſie it ſelfe in ſublime contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) as it may be ſaid to be but in a jayl whiles it reſideth here. And experience confirmeth unto us, that the ſparkes of knowledge we gaine here are not pure, but have the nature of ſalt water, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth the thirſt in them who drink moſt of it; and we ſwallow the pureſt ſtreames like men in a dropſie, who the more they drink are ſtill the greedier of more. Therefore to have this greedineſſe of knowing ſatisfied, and to exerciſe the powers of our ſoul in the pure and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted contemplation of truth, and in the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170053:49"/>ſincere fruition of ſpirituall objects, we muſt have patience untill ſhe arrive unto an other ſtate of life, wherein being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from all corporall feces, impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and contradictions, ſhe may whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give her ſelfe up to that which is her naturall operation, and from whence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulteth her true and perfect delight. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, even they who have attained to the greateſt bleſſings (both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) that this world can afford, yet are farr from being compleatly happy; for that ſtate admitteth no mixture of the contrary: which who was ever yet free from, were his fortune never ſo ſpecious? The very fear of looſing them, that muſt alwaies neceſſarily accompany thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, is ſuch a ſpoonefull of gall to make their whole draught bitter, as that alone muſt needs take off the edge and vigour of the contentment that elſe they might injoy. How little can any man reliſh the objects of delight, which with never ſo great affluence, beſet him round about, when he knoweth a ſharpe and heavy ſword hangeth by a ſlender thred over his head, and at length muſt fall, and ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſever him from them? A little diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, an accidentall feaver, an ill mingled
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170053:50"/>draught (ſuch a one as the miracle of witt and learning, <hi>Lucretius,</hi> met withall) is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to turne the brains of the wiſeſt man that is, and in a few houres to blot out all thoſe notions he hath been in all his life labouring to poſſeſſe himſelfe of, and to render him of a more abject, and deſpicable condition then the meaneſt wretch living that hath but the common uſe of reaſon. The Genius that preſideth over human affaires, delighteth in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall changes, and variation of mens for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, ſo that he who late ſat enthroned in greateſt dignitie, is all of a ſudden preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated head-long unto a condition moſt oppoſit thereunto: he that but yeſterday had all his joyes enlarged, and ſwelled up to their full height by the communication of a perfect and entire freind (without which can there be any true joy?) hath to day loſt the comfort of all that the world can afford him by the irrecoverable loſſe of that one freind. In a word, death grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayly upon him, and incroaching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his outworkes, and by houres reduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him into a narrower circle, at length ſeizeth upon himſelfe, and maketh an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall divorce betweene him, and what was deareſt to him here.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170053:50"/> 3. Our next conſideration then ſhall be to diſcover what will reſult out of our ſwift paſſage through this vale of miſeries, and what impreſſions we ſhall carry with us out of this pilgrimage; ſince we cannot ſuſpect it is a journy aſſigned us in vain, being the ordinary and naturall courſe preſcribed by the wiſe author of nature to all mankinde, and the inevitable through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare for every man in particular. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to proceed on in this method, our third concluſion ſhall be, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever judgement the ſoul once frameth in this life, that judgement and that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will perpetually remain in the ſoul, unleſſe ſome contrary impreſſion be made in it to blot it out; which only hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to expell any former one. For judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affections are cauſed in a man by the impreſſion that the objects make in his ſoul: and all that any agent aymeth at in any operation whatſoever (be it never ſo forcible in action) is but to produce a reſemblance of it ſelfe in the ſubject it worketh upon; and therefore it excludeth nothing that it findeth formerly there (which in our caſe is the ſoul) unleſſe it be ſome ſuch impreſſion as is incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with what it intendeth to effect there;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170053:51"/>or that the ſubject is not large enough, both to retain the old and receive the new; in which caſe the firſt muſt be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out to make room for the latter. But of judgements, and affections, none are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible to one another, but thoſe that are directly oppoſite to one another by contradiction: Therefore only ſuch have power to expell one another; and all that are not ſuch, are immediatly united to the very ſubſtance of the ſoul, which having an infinite capacity, it can never bee filled by any limited objects whatſoever: ſo that they alwaies reſide in the ſoul, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they doe not at all times appear in outward act; which proceedeth from hence, that new and other images are by the fantaſie repreſented to the ſoul, and ſhe ſeemeth to buſy herſelfe onely about what ſhe findeth there, which being but one diſtinct Image at a time (for corporall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans have limited comprehenſions, and are quickly filled with corporal ſpecies) ſhe thereupon ſeemeth to exerciſe but one judgement, or but one affection at a time. But as ſoon as the ſoul ſhall bee releaſed out of the body (which is like a darke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to wall it in) then ſhe will at one and the ſame inſtant actually know and love
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170053:51"/>all thoſe things ſhe knew, and loved in the body; with only this difference, that her knowledge will then be much more diſtinct and perfect, and her affections much more vehement then they were in this life, by reaſon that her conjunction here with reſiſtant matter was a burthen, and a clogge unto her, and hindered the activity and force of her operations. The difference of theſe ſtates, may in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be illuſtrated by a groſſe and materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all example: Repreſent unto your ſelfe a man walled up in a dark tower, that is ſo cloſe, as no ayre nor light can come into it, excepting only at one little hole, and that hole too affordeth no clear and free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the ſight, but hath a thick and muddy glaſſe before it. Now if this man would look upon any of the objects that are about this tower, he muſt get them to be placed over againſt the hole, unto which he muſt lay his eye; and then, he can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne but one at a time, and that but dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neither; and if he will ſee ſeveral bodies, it muſt be by ſo many ſeveral iterated acts as they are in number. But ſuppoſe ſome Earthquake or exterior violence to break a ſunder and throw down to the ground the wals of this tower, leaving the man
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170053:52"/>untouched and unhurt; then at one inſtant, and with one caſt of his eyes, he beholdeth diſtinctly, clearly, and at eaſe, all thoſe ſeveral objects that with ſo much labour and time he took but a miſtaking ſurvey of before.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The fourth conſideration ſhall bee, that after the firſt inſtant wherein the ſoul is ſeparated from the body, ſhe is then in her nature no longer ſubject or liable to any new impreſſion, mutation or change whatſoever. For that which ſhould cauſe any ſuch effect, muſt be either a material or a ſpirituall agent: But a material one cannot work upon it, for that requireth quantity in the patient, whereby it may be applyed unto it to exerciſe its operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon it: Nor can any ſpiritual agent cauſe any ſucceſſion of new alteration; But all that ſpirits work one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is done at once and at one inſtant: which we ſhall diſcerne the clearer by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the reaſon why there is ſucceſſion and time taken up in the alterations that are wrought amongſt material things, for in them, by reaſon of their quantity that cauſeth an extention and diſtance of the parts, the agent, although it have never ſo much diſpoſition and efficacy to worke,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170053:52"/>muſt have his ſeverall parts applyed to I the ſeverall parts of the patient by local motion; which requireth time for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof. And beſides, even in the agent it ſelfe, the groſſeneſſe and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe of the matter giveth an allay, and is a clogge to the activity of the forme; and as it were pulleth it back whiles it is in action. But this is not ſo in ſpirituall ſubſtances, and therefore we may conclude that among them, in the ſame inſtant that the agent is diſpoſed to worke, the action is performed, for on his part there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to retard it, nor is there required a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny locall motion which ſhould take up time; and likewiſe by the ſame reaſon, in the very inſtant that the patient is diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receive any impreſſion, it is wrought in it: And thus, although there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo many agents, and every one of them to performe never ſo many actions, they would be all done, and ended in one and the ſame inſtant.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The next conſideration ſhall be, that thoſe perſons who in this world had ſtrong and predominant affections to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and materiall objects; and dyed in that ſtate, ſhall be eternally miſerable in the next; for by what we have ſaied, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170053:53"/>that thoſe affections will eternally remain in the ſoule; and that after the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of it from the body, they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be blotted out of it, or changed; And the affections of a ſeparated ſoul are much more ardent and vehement then whiles it is in the body. But it is impoſſible they ſhould ever attaine in that ſtate to the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of what they ſo violently covet and love, and yet for its ſake they neglect all other goods whatſoever that they might have, whoſe beauty and excellency not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they plainly diſcerne: they cannot chooſe therefore but execrate themſelves for their fondly miſplaced (yet then eternally neceſſary) affections, and pine away (if ſo I may ſay) with perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all anguiſh and deſpaire of what they ſo impatiently, and enragedly deſire, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can obtain.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The ſixt conſideration ſhall be, that to be happy in the next life, one muſt not ſettle their predominant affections upon any creature whatſoever, or any good that we can naturally attain to the knowledge of in this life. For what natural good ſoever we love or enjoy here, we muſt by death be divorced from, and (as wee have ſaid before) that ſeparation will cauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170053:53"/>ſorrow, becauſe the affections re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unchangeable. And although wee ſhould place our felicity in naturall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or any other intellectuall good whatſoever, yet that cannot ſatisfie the deſires, and fill the capacity of the ſoule, though it be never ſo perfectly injoyed: for they are infinite; and this can be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected but out of particular objects (for the whole created univerſe is but ſo) and therefore they hold no proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together; but the ſoule having nothing elſe to fill it withall, although it ſhould not be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the former mentioned cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſives of prepoſterous affections, yet it cannot be at reſt and quiet, and the thirſt of it ſatiſfied by that drop of water, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the vehement ardor of it.</p>
                  <p>And thus it followeth, that either man was not created for a determinate end, and for a ſtate convenient for his nature, and able to ſatiſfie the originall appeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his ſoule; or at the leaſt, no man can by naturall meanes arrive to the end and period of happineſſe.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. But now to proceed in the purſuance of this method of reaſoning, and to follow hence forward the conduct of a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall guide, ſince nature quitteth us here,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170053:54"/>having lead us on as long as ſhe was able to ſee; we may in the ſeaventh place conſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that God when he created man did not aſſigne him to remaine in the ſtate of pure nature, but did out of his goodneſſe and liberality conferre ſomething upon him that exceeded the ſphere of his nature. For elſe the firſt part of the precedent conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence would follow; which were not only impious, but abſurd to ſay, to whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever conſidereth the infinite goodneſſe, wiſdome and omnipotency of God. For as heat being eſſentiall to fire, cannot but produce heat in whatſoever it hath appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation unto; ſo God being in his owne eſſence goodneſſe it ſelfe, cannot chuſe but doe unto whatſoever proceedeth from him, all that good which the nature of it is capable of; (whether by naturall or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall meanes) and his wiſdome can readily contrive the meanes to bring that to paſſe which his goodneſſe diſpoſeth him to doe; and his omnipotency as eaſily acteth what his other two atributes have projected; ſo that there wanting an infinite object to ſatiſfie the infinite capacity of the ſoule, and without which ſhe muſt be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally miſefable; it remaineth, that he who gave that capacity, muſt alſo afford the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170053:54"/>object, &amp; aſſigne means how to compas &amp; gaine it. All which we have already prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is out of the reach of nature to diſcerne: and therefore it followeth of conſequence, that the author of nature muſt endow man with ſome ſupernaturall giftes, if he be in a fit diſpoſition to receive them, which may bring him to the ſupernaturall end he was created for.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Our eighth concluſion ſhall be that of theſe ſupernaturall gifts, the firſt, and the ground and foundation of all the reſt, is faith. For we have already determined, that we cannot by any naturall meanes attaine to the knowledge of any object that may render us compleatly happy in the next life; And yet ſuch knowledg muſt be had, to the end we may direct our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to gaine the fruition of that object Therefore there is no way left to compaſſe this, but by the inſtructions and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of ſome Maſter, whoſe goodneſſe and knowledge we can no wayes doubt of; by which two perfections in him, we may be ſecure that he neither can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived himſelfe, nor will deceive us. Now the Doctrine that ſuch a Maſter ſhall teach us for ſuch an end, we call faith.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. In the ninth place we muſt determine
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170053:55"/>that this Maſter muſt be God and man. For firſt by our diſcourſe upon naturall principles, we have proved, that to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void miſery in the next life, we muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our ſenſes the content and ſatisfaction that they naturally deſire in corporeall things, and that we muſt withdraw our affections from all materiall objects: And next we have collected that the object we muſt know and love, to be happy, doth exceed the reach and view of any created underſtanding to diſcerne: Therefore we may ſafely conclude that this doctrine ought to be delivered unto us originally by God himſelfe. For after the firſt branch, which is of withdrawing our affections from ſenſible goods; although out of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall principles that doctrine is to be collected, yet that is not a ſufficient meanes to ſettle mankind in generall, in the beliefe of it: For the diſcourſe that proveth it, is ſuch an abſtracted one, as very few are capable of it, being that it requireth both a mature age to be able to reaſon ſo (before which time many dye) and likewiſe ſtrong and vigorous powers of the underſtanding, which we ſee more doe want, then are endowed withall: And beſides, of thoſe that have both yeares
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170053:55"/>and capacity to wield ſuch thoughts, there are ſo few that are not in a manner forced away from ſuch interior recollections by their particular vocations, and the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall neceſſities they are obliged unto; as to beate it out by themſelves is not a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient meanes to ſerve mankind in this caſe. And to thinke that thoſe few, who haveing great partes, may with much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour have attained to the knowledge thereof, ſhould inſtruct others that are ſimpler, and are taken up by other imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and courſes of life, were very irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall; ſince no man, be he never ſo wiſe, is ſuch but may be deceived; and then, how can it be expected that another man ſhould without ſenſible demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beleive his ſingle word in a matter ſo contrary to ſenſe, and wherein he muſt forgoe ſo great contentments and preſent utility?</p>
                  <p>And for the other branch, which is in the inſtructing mankinde concerning the right object that he is to know, and love, to be happy, that is altogether out of the reach of any man whatſoever by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to diſcover; and therefore much leſſe can he in his owne name inſtruct others therein: And if any man ſhould goe about
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170053:56"/>to doe ſo, and to introduce a new doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of faith not formerly heard of, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the arguments for confirmation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of onely out of his owne ratiocination and diſcourſe; that alone were enough to convince him of falſhood; ſince he ſhould thereby undertake to know what were impoſſible for him of himſelfe to attaine to the knowledge of.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it is neceſſary that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the doctrine we muſt believe, the inſtructor of the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s we muſt performe, and the promiser of the happineſſe we may hope for, be God himſelfe; who onely knoweth of himſelfe what is ſayd in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of theſe natures, &amp; who onely is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liable to be deceived, nor can deceive others; as being the prime verity it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe the weakneſſe of our intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall nature is ſuch, whiles we remaine here in our earthly habitations, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our houſes of clay, as we cannot lift up our heavy and drouſie eyes, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily fixe our dimme fight upon the dazel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and indeed inviſible Deity, nor enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an immediate communication with him (like the children of Iſrael, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that Moſes, not God might ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them) it was neceſſary that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170053:56"/>ſhould deſcend to ſome corporal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that might bee more familiar and leſſe dazeling unto us; And none was ſo convenient as humane nature, to the end that he might not onely converſe freely and familiarly with us, and ſo in a gentle and a ſweet manner teach us what wee ſhould doe; but alſo preach unto us by his example, and himſelfe bee our leader in the way that he inſtructed us to take. The concluſion then of this diſcourſe, is, that it was neceſſary, Chriſt, God and man, ſhould come into the world to teach us what to beleive and what to do.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The tenth concluſion ſhall be, that thoſe unto whom Chriſt did immediatly preach this faith, and unto whom he gave commiſſion to preach it unto others, and ſpread it through the world, after hee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to heaven; ought to be believed as firmly as hee himſelfe. The reaſon of this aſſertion is, that their doctrin, though it be delivered by ſecondary mouthes, yet it proceedeth from the ſame fountain: which is God himſelfe, that is the prime verity, and cannot deceive, nor be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But all the difficulty herein is, to know who had this immediate commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Chriſt, &amp; by what ſeal we ſhould
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170053:57"/>diſcern it to have been no forged one. The ſolution of this ariſeth out of the ſame argument which proveth that Chriſt himſelf was God, and that the doctrine he taught was true and divine; which is, the miracles and wonders he did, exceeding the power of nature, and that could be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by none but by God himſelfe: for he being truth it ſelfe, cannot by any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on immediatly proceeding from him, witneſſe and confirm a falſehood: In like manner the Apoſtles doing ſuch admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble works and miracles as neither by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor by art magick could be brought to paſſe, that muſt neceſſarily inferre God himſelfe cooperated with them to juſtifie what they ſaid; it is evident that their doctrine (which was not their own, but received from Chriſt) muſt bee true and Divine.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The eleventh concluſion ſhall bee, that this faith thus taught by Chriſt, and propagated by the Apoſtles, and neceſſary to mankind to believe (as well that part of it which is written, as the whole which is not) dependeth intrinſecally upon the teſtimony of the Catholick Church; which is ordained to conſerve and deliver it from age to age: (By which Catholike
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170053:57"/>Church, I mean the congregation of the faithfull that is ſpread throughtout the whole world) for we have proved before, that the way to the true faith ought to bee open and plain to all men, of all abilities, and in all ages, that have a deſire to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it: and this cannot be but either by the immediate preaching of Chriſt; or elſe by the information (either in writing, or by word of mouth) of them that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it from him, and their delivering it over to others, and ſo from hand to hand untill any particular time you will pitch upon. But from Chriſts own mouth, none could have it, but thoſe who lived in the age when he did: therefore there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no other mens to have it derived down to after ages, then by this delivery over from hand to hand of the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of fathers or elders diſperſed throughout the world, to the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of ſonnes or youngers; which courſe of deducing faith from Chriſt wee call tradition; ſo that this concluſion, proveth that the Church is the conſerver both of the whole doctrine of faith neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for ſalvation, and likewiſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine writ dictated by the Holy Ghoſt, and written by the Prophets, Evangeliſts and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170053:58"/>Apoſtles, which we are alſo bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. And the ſame aſſent that we are to give to the truth of Scriptures (that is to ſay, that the Scriptures wee have are true Scriptures) the very ſame we are to give to other articles of faith propoſed unto us by the Church: for they alike depend of the ſame authority; which is the veracity of the Church propoſing and delivering them unto us to be beleived. And we may as well doubt that the Church hath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Scriptures, as that ſhe hath cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted any article of faith.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. The twelfth concluſion ſhall be, that into the Catholike Church no falſe doctrine in any age can bee admitted or creep in, that is to ſay, no falſe propoſition whatſoever can ever be received and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the Catholike Church as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of faith. For whatſoever the Church believeth as a propoſition of faith, is upon this ground, that Chriſt taught it as ſuch unto the Church hee planted himſelfe, and ſo left it in truſt to bee by it delivered over to the next age. And the reaſon why the preſent Church believeth any propoſition to be of faith, is, becauſe the immediate preceding Church of the age before, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170053:58"/>it as ſuch. And ſo you may drive it on from age to age untill you come to the Apoſtles and Chriſt. Therefore to have any falſe propoſition of faith admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Church in any age, doth Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that all they of that age muſt unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly conſpire to deceive their children and youngers, telling them that they were taught by their fathers to believe, as of faith, ſome propoſition which indeed they were not. Which being impoſſible (as it will evidently appear to any prudent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſhall reaſonably ponder the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) that ſo many men ſpread throughout the whole world, ſo different in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular intereſts and ends, and of ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſpoſitions and natures, ſhould all agree together in the forgery of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe lye; it is impoſſible that any falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſhould creep into the Church.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe the force of this argument may peradventure not appear at the firſt ſight to your Ladyſhip, that happily hath not had much occaſion to make deep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the certainty that muſt needs be in the aſſeveration of any hiſtory of matter of fact, ſubject to the ſenſe, which ſhall be made by a great company of men ſo diſtant from one another, and of ſuch
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170053:59"/>different intereſts and affections as they cannot conſpire together in the forgery of a falſehood; But that you may happily think, ſince any one man is lyable to bee deceived, or out of ſome indirect end may be induced to deceive another, it is alſo poſſible that a multitude of men (be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great) conſiſting of particular men, may alſo deceive or bee deceived: I will therefore for a further declaration of this matter, propoſe for the thirteenth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that faith thus delivered, is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely more certain and infallible then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny natural ſcience whatſoever. And yet ſciences are ſo certain (I mean ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of experience and demonſtration) as he were not a rationall man that ſhould refuſe his aſſent unto them: And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he would incurre the like cenſure that ſhould not yeeld credence to faith, in this manner propoſed unto him. In the proofe of this concluſion I muſt uſe two words appropriated to philoſophy (to wit matter and forme) which is contrary to my intention at the firſt, which was to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from all termes of artificial learning, and make onely a familiar diſcourſe that ſhould require no precedent help of ſtudy, but onely a clear and ſtrong judgement
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170053:59"/>(ſuch as yours is) to weigh the ſtrength of the reaſons: But I am the leſſe ſcrupulous to avoid theſe words, becauſe I know your Ladyſhip underſtandeth what is meaned by them; and they have often oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred in our diſcourſes. To come then to the examination of this concluſion, I ſay, that faith dependeth on theſe two propoſitions; firſt, that whatſoever God ſaith is true; Next, that God ſaid this (whatſoever it be) that is delivered thus by the tradition of the Church. For the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe aſſertions, there is no doubt made by any ſide; ſince all agree that God being the prime verity, whatſoever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth immediately from him muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be more infallible then any col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections made from creatures either by experience or ratiocination of men.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond aſſertion I ſhall alſo prove to be more infallible then any ſuch collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; in this manner. Among material things, that are ſubject to time and place, and are here in the ſphere of contraries, and of action and paſſion, although the lawes that govern them are in the generall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine (elſe no ſcience could be acquired of them) yet in the particular they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to contingency and defection from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170053:60"/>thoſe lawes; which contingency doth proceed from the reſiſtance of the matter, and the contagion and leproſy (if ſo I may ſay) that the matter infecteth the forme withall; which were it not for that, would alwayes conſtantly worke the ſame effect in all occaſions: and according as the forme hath in particular more or leſſe predominance over the matter, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingency and defect in them from the true nature of that body conſidered in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, is the greater or the leſſer. Let us illuſtrate this by an example: According to the ordinary doctrine of Philoſophers in the Schooles, we collect by many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular experiences, that the nature of fire proceeding from the forme of it, is to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend; and of them we frame a generall doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that fire is the lighteſt of all the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that his naturall place is above them all: yet we ſee that when the forme of fire is introduced into groſſe and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall matter, it is wreſted from his owne naturall inclination, and is forced, inſteed of aſcending, then to deſcend; as when wood, iron, earth, coale, and ſuch other terreſtriall matter is ſet on fire: And it is more or leſſe violented from his naturall place, according as the ſubject it
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170053:60"/>reſideth in, hath more or leſſe power over it, and is more or leſſe materiall: for it ſheweth more of his levity and naturall propenſion to aſcend, when it ſetteth an oyly, or ayery ſubſtance on fire, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up in flames, then when meeting with a more materiall &amp; terreſtriall ſubſtance, as wood, it turneth it into a coale. Now to apply this to our purpoſe, I ſay, that of all formes whatſoever that are joyned to matter, the nobleſt and moſt elevated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the faeculency of matter, is the ſoule of man: for it is not onely the forme of the nobleſt materiall creature that is; but beſides that, it is ſo full of efficacy as it eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> overfloweth the capacity of matter, which not being able to imbibe (as I may ſay) and take it up all, it hath a particular ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence belonging to its ſelfe; from whence Philoſophers prove the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of it. Therefore we may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that mankind, in the originall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petences and naturall deſires of his ſoule, is leſſe ſubject to contingency, and more ſecure from having his nature corrupted and perverted from his due courſe, then any other materiall creature whatſoever is in the performance of thoſe actions that proceed from the activity of his
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170053:61"/>forme; and ſo conſequently, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in generall, proceedeth moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and infallibly to the purſuance thereof; and it is impoſſible it ſhould fall off from its owne nature, and ſuffer that to be extinguiſhed in it; although in ſome particulars, by the immerſion in matter, and the terrene habitation it dwelleth in, ſome ſoule may be drawne, or rather wreſted to a contrary byas unto that which originally nature implanted in it. Now the primary originall naturall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petence of mans ſoule, is the love of truth; which it vehemently deſireth, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes unquiet and ardent in the ſearch of it upon what occaſion ſoever, and is never appeaſed and at eaſe, untill ſhe have found it out; which ſhe no ſooner hath done, but the violence ſhe was in is calmed; ſhe is contented, and ſhe ſetleth her ſelfe to repoſe, as having arrived to her center and naturall place of reſt; wherein ſhe continueth enjoying the purchaſe ſhe hath made, untill ſome new occaſion of diſquiſition ſtir her up againe; in which ſhe uſeth the ſame induſtry and eagerneſſe as before. And thus we plainly ſee that the acquiſition of truth is that which the ſoule in every action naturlaly aymeth
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170053:61"/>at, as fire doth to aſcend; &amp; deteſteth falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as flames ſuffer violence to be rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated downewards. Therefore, although any particular man may have his ſenſes or fantaſie ſo depraved as to take imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and maymed impreſſions of outward objects; or the powers of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo weake as to make prepoſterous and diſorderly collections out of them; or his judgement ſo miſguided by preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of any affection or particular end, as he may in himſelfe be deceived, and feed his ſoule with falſehood inſteede of truth; or elſe, that finiſter reſpects and intereſts, or ſordide apprehenſions of commodity to himſelfe, meeting with a ſoule ſo diſpoſed and wrought upon by the ſenſuall paſſions tyranniſing over it, as to cauſe him to ſwallow thoſe bayter, may make him employ the faculties of his underſtanding and the powers of his ſoule, contrary unto their naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, to the maintaining of a lye, and induſtriouſly to deceive others: yet it is impoſſible that all mankind, or ſuch a multitude of men as containe in them all the variety of diſpoſitions and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons incident to the nature of man, and that are diſperſed throughout the world,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170053:62"/>ſo as they can have no communion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether whereby they might infect one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, nor can have finiſter ends common alike to them all, which ſhould invite them to conſpire together to forge a falſehood: it is impoſſible (I ſay) that ſuch a company of men ſhould ſo degenerate from their owne nature (which is to love truth) as they ſhould of themſelves invent a lye (and that in ſo important a matter as faith is) and concurre to deceive the world of men that ſhould come after them in things of such nature, as their deceipt muſt of neceſſity damne for all eternity both themſelves and all them that ſhall receive that lye from them, and take it upon their credit: without which unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſpiracy of one whole age of men throughout all the world, we proved in our laſt concluſion that no falſe propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could be admitted into the Church as an article of faith. In a word, this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall defection of all mankind from truth, is more impoſſible, then that all one entire element, or any primigeniall nature ſhould abſolutely periſh or looſe its original pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety; as for all the fire in the world to be corrupted and forſake his heat &amp; levity, &amp; ſo conſequently to have no more fire in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170053:62"/>nature: all which followeth of what is ſaid above. And thus I conceive I have made good the aſſertion that hath begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all this diſcourſe upon the thirteenth head; which is, that faith conſerved in the Catholick Church, and delivered by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſucceſſion and generall tradition, is more certaine and more infallible then any naturall ſcience whatſoever: for natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſciences being grounded upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defectibility of the natures of thoſe things from whence thoſe ſciences are collected; and faith depending upon the indefecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of human nature, which is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more noble then they, and whoſe forme is elevated beyond the reach of matter (whereas theirs is comprehended and ſhutt up within the wombe of matter, and which is indeed the end and period of all their natures, and of all the whole materiall world) it followeth of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that faith muſt be leſſe ſubject to contingency, and leſſe liable to error then naturall ſciences are. And they being univerſall, infallible and certaine; faith muſt be ſo too; and more, if more may be.</p>
                  <p>But this is not enough, our diſquiſition muſt not reſt here: We muſt not content
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170053:63"/>our ſelves in this divine affaire and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall doctrine with a certitude de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending only upon naturall cauſes. The wiſdome of God proportioneth out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruent meanes to bring on every thing to their proper end; and according to the nobility of the effect that he will have produced, he ordaineth equivalent noble cauſes. Therefore, mans obtaining beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude being the higheſt end that any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can arrive unto, and altogether ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, it requireth ſupernaturall cauſes to bring us to that end, and a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall infallibility to ſecure us in that jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. We muſt not onely have a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall way to travell in (which is faith) but alſo a ſupernaturall aſſurance of the right way, unto the diſcovery of which, all that we have already ſaid, doth neceſſarily conduce; for Gods providence that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth all things ſweetly, will not in any generall affaire introduce into the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial world any ſupernaturall effect, untill the naturall cauſes be firſt diſpoſed fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly to cooperate on their partes; and then he never faileth of his. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when a naturall creature is to be produced into being, the father and the mother muſt both concurre in contribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170053:63"/>all that is in their power, to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a child; and yet we are ſure the ſoule to be produced hath no dependence of them; yet notwithſtanding, without their precedentaction no new ſoule would be: but when the matter is fittingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the mothers wombe, he never miſſeth creating of a ſoule in that body; which is not ſo able an effect, and as much requiring the omnipotency of God, as the creating of nothing all the materiall world; and yet we may ſay that the matter when it is arrived to its laſt diſpoſition for the reception of ſuch a forme, may in a manner claime that miraculous action depending of his omnipotency; ſince for mankind he created the reſt of the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all world, and therefore there ought to be as certaine and neceſſary cauſes for the productio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, as there are for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of other materiall things, which we ſee doe ſeldome miſſe in any when the matter is fitly diſpoſed for the reception of their ſeverall formes. And ſo in like manner we may rationally conclude, that in this high and ſupernaturall buſineſſe of delivering over from hand to hand a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall doctrine to bring mankind to the end it was created for, he will firſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170053:64"/>have all the naturall cauſes fittingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the ſecure and infallible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that worke: and then, that he will adde and infuſe into them ſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural gift whereby to give them yet further a ſupernaturall aſſurance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility; which they may with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confidence in his unlimited goodneſs, expect and claim at his divine hand, when they are reduced to that ſtate as is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the reception of ſuch a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall gift.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Our fourteenth concluſion therefore ſhall be, that God hath given to his Church thus compoſed, the holy Ghoſt, to confirm it in the true faith, and to preſerve it from error, and to Illuminate the underſtanding of it in right diſcerning the true ſenſe of thoſe Myſteries of faith that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the cuſtody of it, and to worke ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall effects of devotion and ſanctifie in that Church. And this I prove thus; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the doctrine of Chriſt is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical, and aymeth at the working of an effect, which is the reduction of mankind to beatitude: and that mankinde compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth not onely thoſe that lived in that age, when he preached, but alſo all others that ever were ſince, or ſhall be till the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170053:64"/>end of the world: It is apparent that to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh that end, it was neceſſary Chriſt ſhould ſo effectually imprint his doctrine in their hearts whom he delivered it unto, as it might upon all occaſions and at all times infallibly expreſſe it ſelfe in action, and in the delivery of it over from hand to hand, ſhould in vertue and ſtrength of the firſt operation, produce ever after like effects in all others. Now to have this compleatly performed, it was to bee done both by exteriour and by interiour means, proportionable to the ſenſes without, and to the ſoule within. The outward means were the miracles that hee wrought, of which himſelfe ſaith, <hi>If I had not wrought thoſe workes that no man elſe ever did, they were not guilty of ſinne, but now, they have no excuſe:</hi> (or to this purpoſe) and he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the Apoſtles they ſhould do greater then thoſe. And that miracles are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per inſtruments to plant a new doctrine and faith withall, the Apoſtle witneſſeth, when he ſaith that miracles are wrought for the unfaithfull, not for the faithful, and God himſelfe told Moſes that hee would once do ſome prodigy in his favour, that the people might for ever after beleive what he ſaid to them. But it is manifeſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170053:65"/>by the fall of the Apoſtles themſelves, that onely this exteriour means of miracles is not ſufficient to engraft ſupernatural faith deep enough in mens hearts, when as they upon Chriſts Paſſion, not onely for fear, through human frailty denied their maſter, but had even the very conceit and belief of his doctrine exiled out of their hearts and underſtanding, notwithſtanding all the miracles they had ſeen him work in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt four years time they continually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with him: which appeareth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the diſcourſe of the Diſciples going to Emaus, when they ſaid <hi>we hoped &amp;c.</hi> and expreſſed their ſadneſſe for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſucceſſe to their expectation; and by ſaint Thomas his ſaying that he would not believe his reſurrection unleſs he ſaw him, and put his fingers into his wounds &amp;c. And by the reſt of the Apoſtles that were ſo long before they would believe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as having given over the thought of his divinity, and after his death conſidered him but as a pure man like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. Therefore it was neceſſary that ſome inward light ſhould bee given them, ſo clear, and ſo ſtrong, and ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, as the ſenſes ſhould not be able to prevail againſt it, but that it ſhould over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowingly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170053:65"/>poſſeſſe and fill all their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and their ſouls, and make them break out in exteriour actions correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the ſpirit that ſteered them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And the reaſon is evident: for while: on the one ſide the ſenſes diſcerne, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, miracles wrought in confirmation of a doctrine; and on the other ſide, the ſame ſenſes doe ſtifly contradict the very poſſibility of the doctrine which thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles teſtify; the ſoul within, having no aſſiſtance beyond the natural powers ſhee hath belonging originally unto her, is in great debate and anxiety which way to give her aſſent; and though reaſon doe prevail to give it to the party of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miracles, yet it is with great timidity. But if it happen that the courſe of thoſe miracles be ſtopped; then the particular ſeeming impoſſibilities of the propoſed faith remaining alwaies alike lively in their apprehenſion, and the miracles wrought to confirme it reſiding but in the memory, and the repreſentations of them wearing out daily more and more, and the preſent ſenſes and fantaſy grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proportionably ſtronger and ſtronger, and withall objecting continually new doubts about the reality of thoſe miracles,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170053:66"/>it cannot be expected otherwiſe, but that the aſſent of the ſoul ſhould range it ſelfe on the ſide of the impoſſibilities appearing to the preſent ſenſes, and renounce the doctrine formerly confirmed by miracles, unleſſe ſome inward and ſupernaturall light be given her to diſperſe all the miſts that the ſenſes raiſe againſt the truth of the doctrine. Now the infuſion of this light and fervour, we call the giving of the holy Ghoſt, which Chriſt himſelfe foreknowing how neceſſary it was, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them, aſſuring them that he would procure his father to ſend them the holy Ghoſt, the ſpirit of truth, that ſhould for ever remain among them, and within them, and ſuggeſt unto their memory and inſtruct them in the right underſtanding of the faith he had preached unto them. And this was propheſied long before, of the ſtate of the law of grace by Hieremy, whoſe authority S. Paul bringeth to prove that the law of the Goſpel was to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the holy Ghoſt in mens hearts and in their mindes, and accordingly, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the faithful of the Corinthians, <hi>The faith of Chriſt, not written with inke, but with the ſpirit of God; nor graven in ſtony tables, but in the fleshy ones of their hearts.</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170053:66"/>And in performance of this propheſy &amp; of Chriſts promiſe, the hiſtory telleth us that on the tenth day after the aſcenſion of Chriſt, when all his diſciples (who were then all his Church, and were to preach and deliver it to all the world) were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together, the holy Ghoſt was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, and that in ſo full a meaſure, as they not onely were confirmed ſo perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their faith as they never after admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the leaſt vacillation therein, but they immediately, caſting away all other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and thoughts, were inflamed with admirable love of God, and broke out into his prayſes, and into a vehement ardor of teaching and converting others; and when by reaſon of that zeal of theirs, any thing happened to them contrary to fleſh and blood, &amp; humane nature (as perſecutions, ignominies, corporall puniſhments, and even death it ſelfe) they not only ſhunned it, as before, but greedily rann to meet and imbrace it, and joyed, and gloryed in it: all which were effects of the holy Ghoſt reſiding in them, and filling their minds, and governing their ſoules. Where upon by the way we may note, that in what Church ſoever we find not a ſtate of life for ſanctitie and neer union with God,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170053:67"/>and contempt of worldly and tranſitory things, raiſed above the pitch of nature and morality, we may conclude the holy Ghoſt inhabiteth not there: for every agent produceth effects proportionable to the dignity of it, and the excellency of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſe ſhineth eminently in the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of its effects. Now that this gift of the holy Ghoſt is to remaine with the Church as long as the Church remaineth, to illuminate it with the ſpirit of truth, and to give it a ſupernaturall and divine unction, will appear manifeſtly upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the cauſe why the holy Ghoſt was to be given at the firſt, which remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alwaies the ſame, and therefore the ſame effect muſt alwaies follow; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, Chriſt promiſed his Church upon his aſcending into heaven, that he would alwaies remaine with them untill the end of the world, to wit, by this holy ſpirit; for he was then at the point of withdrawing his corporeall preſence from them.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Our next concluſion ſhall be, that this Church or congregation of men ſpread over the world, conſerving and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the faith of Chriſt from hand to hand, is even in its owne nature perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170053:67"/>in time, and cannot faile as long as mankind remaineth in the world. This needeth no further proofe then that which we have already made; which is derived from the neceſſity of ſupernaturall faith to bring mankind to the end it was creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and that there is no meanes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver this faith to mankind in the ages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, but by the tradition of the Church; and therefore as long as man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind laſteth, this meanes muſt be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Yet in this way of reaſoning that I uſe, we are to examine our concluſions as well by the genuine and orderly cauſes that beget them, and by their owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular principles, as to aſſent unto them for the neceſſity that we ſee in them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the end that they are referred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: And when we haue retrived thoſe, and evidently diſcerned their force, it giveth an admirable content and ſatiſfaction to the underſtanding. Thus then: as philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers conclude that it is impoſſible any whole ſpecies or kind of beaſts ſhould ever be utterly exterminated and deſtroyed, that is diffuſed up and downe over the whole face of the earth, becauſe the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude of the univerſe is greater then the variety of cauſes can be from which ſuch
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170053:68"/>a generall and entire corruption muſt proceed: In like manner we may confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conclude, that it is impoſſible any depraved affections ſhould ſo univerſally prevaile, and ſo abſolutely raigne in mens mindes throughout the whole world, as would be requiſite to extirpate and roote out a doctrine univerſally ſpread over it all, that was at the firſt taught and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with ſuch ſeales of truth as the miracles that Chriſt and the apoſtles wrought, that in its ſelfe is ſo pure and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the ſeedes that every man find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſowed, even by nature, in his owne ſoule; that worketh ſuch admirable effects as the reformation of manners in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; that withdraweth mens affections from humane and worldly contentments, and carrieth them with a ſweet violence to intellectuall objects, and to hopes of immortality and happineſſe in another life; that preſcribeth lawes for happy liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, even in this world, to all men of what condition ſoever, either publicke or private, as working a moderation in mens affections to the commodities and goods of this life, which elſe in nature is apt to blind mens mindes, and is the cauſe of all miſchiefs and evills; and laſtly, that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170053:68"/>over from hand to hand, from worlds of fathers to worlds of ſonnes, with ſuch care and exactneſſe as greater cannot be imagined, and as it is requiſite to the importance of that affaire; which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely beyond all others, as on which the ſalvation and damnation of mankind wholly dependeth. Now, unto theſe ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſiderations let us adde the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which Chriſt made to his Church, that the gates of hell ſhould not prevaile againſt it; and I thinke we have ſufficiently maintained that the Church of Chriſt in which the true doctrine of Chriſt is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, can never faile, but muſt infallibly continue unto the worlds end. Thus hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proved, that a ſupernatural doctrine is neceſſary to bring mankind to beatitude, that Chriſt taught this doctrine, that from him the Church received it, and is the ſacrary in which it is conſerved; that this Church cannot erre in the tradition of this doctrine, that beſides the infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, this Church is perpetuall; It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth now that we cloſe up this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe by applying all theſe premiſes unto the queſtion in hand; which is, where we ſhall find out this infallible Church, that by it we may gaine the knowledge of the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170053:69"/>true ſaith of Chriſt, whereby we are to be ſaved.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. For this end our ſixteenth and laſt concluſion ſhall be, that the congregation of men ſpread over the world, joyning in communion with the Church of Rome, is the true Catholike Church, in which is conſerved and taught the true ſaving faith of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The truth of this concluſion will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bringing any new proofes appeare evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently by reflecting upon what we have ſaid, and onely examining whether the Romane Church be ſuch a one as we have determined the true Church of Chriſt muſt be; or whether the notes which we may inferre out of our diſcourſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long inſeparably to the true Church, may not rather with more reaſon be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of ſome other then of that in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the ſee of Rome? This point after theſe grounds layed, requireth no very ſubtill diſquiſition, but is diſcerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble even by the weakeſt ſights: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this way of arguing appeareth to me moſt ſatiſfactory and contentfull, when taking the whole body of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into ſurvey, and beginning with the firſt and remoteſt conſiderations of it,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170053:69"/>we drive the difficulties ſtill before us; and purſuing of them orderly, at every ſteppe we eſtabliſh a ſolid principle, and ſo become ſecure of the truth and certainty of all we leave behind us; which courſe, although it may at the firſt fight appear to be a great way about, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but ſuperficially upon the matter we may ſeeme to meete with difficulties which concerne not our queſtion; yet in the effect we ſhall perceive it is the moſt ſummary method of handling any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie; and the onely meanes to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured of the truth of what we conclude, and that will recompence the precedent difficulties by making the concluſion (which is the knot of the affair) plaine, eaſie, and open. I ſay then firſt, that unity of doctrine in matters of faith is inſeparable from the Roman Church, and can never be found in any other: it onely, having a preciſe and determinate rule of faith. For it hath believed in every age, all that hath bin plainly and poſitively taught unto it by their Fathers as the doctrine of faith derived from Chriſt; and admitteth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther article whatſoever as an article of faith. Whereas on the other ſide, all other Chriſtian Churches among us that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170053:70"/>reformation, having no certaine and common rule of faith, but every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man governing himſelfe in this matter by the collections of his owne braine, and by his owne private under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and interpretation of Scripture (which onely he acknowledgeth as the entire rule of faith) it muſt conſequently follow, that according to the variety of their tempers and judgements, there muſt bee a variety and difference of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and beliefes; which difference of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per happening for the moſt part betweene every two men that are, it likewiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſcarce any two ſhould in all particulars of their opinions agree together. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly wee ſee by experience, that ſcarce any two authors, out of the Roman Church, that have written of matters of faith have agreed in their tenets, but rather have diſſented in fundamentall doctrine, and have inveighed againſt one another in their writings with great vehemence &amp; bitteſnes. Whereas on the other ſide, the Doctors of the Roman Church in al times, in all places, and of all tempers have agreed unanimouſly in all matters of faith; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the mean time, ſeverall of them, have in divers other points great debates
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170053:70"/>againſt one another, and purſue them with much ſharpneſſe: which ſtrongly confirmeth the ground upon which we frame this obſervation.</p>
                  <p>But to inſiſt a little further upon this materiall and important conſideration; it is evident that the proceeding of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers openeth the gate to all diſſenſion, ſchiſme, irreverence, pride of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hereſie, &amp; ruine of Chriſtian Religion: for to juſtifie the new births of their rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious braines, the firſt ſtroake of their pen muſt be, to lay a taint of ignorance &amp; error upon the whole current of ancient fathers and Doctors of the Church, and generall Councells, and to blaſt their authority; which is ſo preciſely contrary to their doctrine, whoſe names and records ought to be ſacred with poſterity. Which when they have done; to ſettle a conſtant and like beliefe in all men, they give no gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and certaine rule; but leaving every man to the dictamens of his owne private judgement, according to the ſeverall tempers and circumſtances (as wee ſaid before) that ſway every ſingle man in particular, there muſt reſult (which we ſee by experience) as great a variety of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170053:71"/>opinions as thoſe are different. And laſtly ſince they quarrell at Catholickes beliefe in thoſe points where they differ from them, becauſe they captivate their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings with reverence to what the Church propoſeth and teacheth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by admit into their beliefe articles which may ſeeme abſurd to common ſenſe; they may as well with preſumptuous hands graſpe at, and ſeeke to pluck up the very foundations of Chriſtian Religion; as namely the Doctrine of the Trinity, and of the incarnation of Chriſt, and of the reſurrection and ſtate of life of the future world: ſince there are greater ſeeming contradictions in them (eſpecially in the two firſt) then in thoſe myſteries the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers cavill at.</p>
                  <p>In the next place we may conſider, that as infallibility is pretended by the Roman Church alone, ſo it is apparently entayled upon it: for we have proved that no meanes or circumſtance, either morall, naturall or ſupernaturall, is wanting in it to beget infallibility in matters of faith. Whereas on the other ſide, from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers owne poſition we inferre by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, that their doctrine cannot be hoped (even by themſelves) to be infallible,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170053:71"/>and therefore they that ſhall ſubmitt their underſtanding to their conduct, though they believe without controverſy all they ſay, muſt needs (even by reaſon of what is taught them) floate alwaies in a great deale of incertitude, and anxious apprehenſion and feare of error. For they looking upon the Church, but with pure humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and as an ordinary company of men, will have it lyable to miſtaking, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the naturall imbecillity of mens witts and underſtandings, and of humane paſſions, and negligence, and other ſuch defects and weakneſſes which every man is by nature ſubject unto: Againſt which they produce no antidote to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and ſecure themſelves from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection &amp; taint they lay upon the Church. For, if they will have the conferences of ſeverall paſſages of Scripture to be that which muſt give light in the ſeverall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted obſcurities; what eminency have theſe few late reformers ſhewne, either in knowledge of tongues, inſight into anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, profoundneſſe in ſciences, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and ſanctity of life, which hath not ſhined admirably more (not to taxe them here of the contrary) in multitudes of the adverſe party? And none will deny
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170053:72"/>but theſe are the likelyeſt meanes to gaine a right intelligence of the true and deepe ſence of Scriptures. And beſides, we may obſerve that the reaſon why they deny the ſeverall articles wherein they differ from the Catholicke Church, is becauſe it teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a doctrine which is repugnant to ſence, and of hard digeſtion to philoſophy; both which are uncompetent judges of divine and ſupernaturall truths: And whoſoever ſteereth by their compaſſe, cannot hope for infallibility in a matter that tranſcendeth their reach.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly we may conſider that the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of the Church in regard of place (which is neceſſary, to the end that all mankind may have ſufficient meanes to gaine knowledge of the true faith) can be attributed to none but to the Roman Catholick Church; which onely is diffuſed throughout the whold world; whereas all others are circled in with narrow limits of particular provinces; And even within them, the profeſſors ſcarce agree among themſelves in any point of doctrine, but in oppoſing the Roman Church.</p>
                  <p>And yet further; beſides this want of vniverſality in regard of place; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion taught by the reformers, hath yet a
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170053:72"/>greater reſtriction then that: for even in its own nature, it is not for all ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and for all capacities: whereas the true ſaving faith to bring men to beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ought to be obvious to all mankind, and open as well to the ſimple as to the learned. For ſince they lay the Scriptures as the firſt and higheſt principle, from whence they deduce all to that ought to be believed; And that in all arts and ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the primary and fundamentall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples therof ought to bee throughly known by them that aſpire to the perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thoſe ſciences; it followeth that one muſt have an exact knowledge of the learned tongues to examine punctually the true ſenſe of the Scriptures; and that one muſt bee perfectly verſed in logick to bee able to reaſon ſolidly, and to deduce true conſequences from certaine principles (for want of which, we find by experience that great controverſies ariſe daily among the learnedſt men; which would not bee, if the force of conſequences were of their owne nature eaſily diſcernable) and one muſt be throughly skilled in naturall phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy and Metaphyſickes, ſince unto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing contradictions in ſubjects of thoſe ſciences, they reduce moſt of their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170053:73"/>againſt the ſupernaturall truths that Catholickes believe. And laſtly, one muſt be indowed with an excellent judgement and ſtrong naturall witt, to be able to wield and make good uſe of theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons; without which they would but advance him the faſter to ruine and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious error. With which excellencyes, how few are there in the world fairely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, it is evident that the Roman Catholicke Church onely hath had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and uninterrupted ſucceſſion of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Doctors, and tradition of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine from age to age, which we have eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed as the onely meanes to derive downe the true faith from Chriſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is apparent all others have had late beginnings from unworthy cauſes: And yet, even in this little while, have not beene able to mantaine themſelves for one age throughout (or ſcarce for any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of an age) in one tenor of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, or forme of Eccleſiaſticall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Laſtly we may conſider how the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the holy Ghoſt his inhabiting in the Church, in regard of manners, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hearts of men his living temples, ſhineth eminently in the Catholick
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170053:73"/>Church, and is not ſo much as to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in any other whatſoever. For where this holy ſpirit raigneth, it giveth a burning love of God (as we have touched before) and a vehement deſire of approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto him as near as may be. Now, the ſoule of man moveth towards God, not by corporeall ſtepps and progreſſions, but by intellectuall actions; the higheſt of which, are mentall prayer and contemplation; in which exerciſes, a man ſhall advance the more, by how much he is the more ſequeſtred from the thought and care of any worldly affaires, and hath his paſſions quieted within him, and is abſtracted from communication with materiall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and is untyed from human intereſts, and (according to the counſailes of Chriſt in the Goſpell) hath caſt off all ſollicitude of the future, and remitteth himſelfe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the providence of God, living in the world as though he were not in it, wholly intent to contemplation, when the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour part of Charity calleth him not downe to comply with the neceſſity of his Neighbours. This forme of life we ſee continually practiſed in the Catholick Church by multitudes of perſons of both ſexes, that through extreame deſire of ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proaching
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170053:74"/>as neare unto God as this life will permitt, doe baniſh themſelves from all their friends, kindred, and what elſe in the world was naturally deareſt unto them; and either retire into extreame ſolitudes, or ſhut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up for ever within the narrow limits of a ſtraight Monaſtery and little cell; where having renounced all the intereſt and propriety in the goods of this world, and uſing no more of them then is neceſſary for the ſuſtenance of their exhauſted bodyes (which they mortifie with great abſtinences, watchings and other auſterities, that they may bring them into ſubjection; and roote out, as much as may be, the very fewell of concupiſcence and paſſions) and having of their owne accord barred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all propriety of diſpoſing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any action, and renounced even the freedome of their will; and thus in ſumme, having taken an eternall farewell of all the joyes and delights that this world can afford, and that carnall men would bee ſo loth to forgoe for any little while; yet by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall joyes that they find in their prayer and contemplation (unto which all theſe actions of retrenchment from ſuperfluities, or outward ſolaces, doe ſerve as a ladder to aſcend unto the top of it) they live ſo happily, and chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and with ſuch tranquillity of mind, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170053:74"/>upon occaſions ſay ſo much of the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of their blyſſe, as it is aparent they enjoy there the hundred fold that Chriſt promiſed in this life. Nor can it be objected that men uſually betake themſelves to this courſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious life, upon being diſtempered by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, or for the ill ſucceſſe and traverſes they have had in affaires of the world, or out of ſimplicity and weakneſſe of underſtanding; ſince it is evident that this angelicall forme of living hath ever heene practiſed by perſons of the beſt compoſed and cheerfulleſt diſpoſitions; and by multitudes of ſuch is and hath beene imbraced; and that in the world overflowed with all the bleſſings it could afford them; and were of ſtrongeſt parts of underſtanding and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> judgement; and were moſt eminent in learning So that it is apparent they had no other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive thereunto, but purely the love of God and fervour of devotion: which being an effect of the holy Ghoſt reſiding in their hearts; to his inſpirations and admirable wayes of working in thoſe his temples of fleſh and blood, theſe extraordinary effects are to be imputed. Whereas on the other ſide no ſuch examples, or ſupernaturall forme of life, are to be mett withall in any other Church whatſoever: Rather they diſclaime from them; and like men of this world (which is the expreſſion
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170053:75"/>that Chriſt uſeth in the Goſpell to deſigne thoſe that are not of his Church) not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcerne things of the ſpirit, but being blinded with the luſtre of them, too great for their weake eyes, they neglect and diſdaine them, and imagine that all Chriſtian perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſteth in an ordinary humane morall life: which is the uttermoſt period that any among them ſeek to attaine unto. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may hence conclude that they have no interior worker among them, more ſublime then their owne humane diſcourſes and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and that ſupernaturall ſanctity (an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the holy Ghoſt) is confined onely to the Catholick Church.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, wee may obſerve by daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, how thoſe perſons that addict themſelves to ſuch an extraordinary way of life, doe abſolutely prove the very beſt, or the worſt of mankind; the one excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in admirable piety, fervour of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, abſtraction and ſanctity of life, and ſome of them ſoaring up to a pitch even above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the other abounding in all ſorts of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, wickedneſſe and diſſolution of manners, till at length their hearts become even harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt correction, and all ſence of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things; whereas it ordinarily happeneth that the moſt flagitious men among thoſe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170053:75"/>who live in a vulgar worldly eſtate of life, doe upon occaſions frequently receive notable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions from divine objects, to the amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and change of their diſſolute courſe. And this being a conſtant &amp; certaine effect noted at all times and in all places, it muſt be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a conſtant and powerfull cauſe: which can be no other then the neere approaching of thoſe perſons to the originall fountaine of ſanctity &amp; goodneſſe; which being like a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire, worketh vehement effects in them, according to the diſpoſition they are in, and to the neareneſſe that they have unto that fire: ſo that as the ſunbeames (which are the authors of life and foecundity to all plants and vegetables) ſhining upon a tree that hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſolide rootes in the earth, maketh it budd, flouriſh, and beare fruit, and on the other ſide, if it be weakely rooted, their heate and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration upon that tree maketh it the ſooner to wither and die: And as the fire ſendeth an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of heate into a pot of water that is ſymply applyed unto it, but if that pot be ſet in a veſſell of Snow or Ice, and ſo be held over the fire, it driveth into the center the cold of the Snow formerly diffuſed without, and in a very ſhort ſpace turneth that water into Ice, which elſe might have ſtayed there long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without congealing: in like manner, they who being rooted in Charity, approach
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170053:76"/>to that divine Sunne, doe flouriſh and bring forth excellent, and oftentimes ſupernaturall fruites of devotion, fervour, and ſanctitie; but thoſe who have depraved affections ſo invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roning the roots of their hearts, as that the ſoyle of Charity cannot introduce her nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſappe into them; and whoſe ſoules are compaſſed in with the Ice of ſenſuality and carnall cogitations; if they come within the beames of this holy Sunne, or within the heate of this ſanctifying fire, they doe but wither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſooner, and their hearts grow day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more to be Ice, till at length (like that of Pharaoh, amidſt the wondrous workes of the lord, happy to others) they become miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable and ſtony.</p>
                  <p>And againe we ſee, that thoſe who having addicted themſelves wholly to ſuch a courſe of ſeraphicall life, and that being alwaies vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently intent to the love and contemplation of the prime verity, and that having no other object for their actions or thoughts; doe thereby (as we may reaſonably conceive) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach neareſt to God allmighty, and draw immediately from him (who is the fountaine of light and truth) ſtrongeſt emanations and cleereſt influences to illuſtrate their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and inflame their affections: thoſe perſons (I ſay) have ever beene moſt earneſt in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170053:76"/>the maintenance of thoſe points of the Roman doctrine which are moſt repugnant to ſenſe; as in particular, of that of the reall preſence of Chriſts body in the bleſſed Sacrament; unto which all other ſacraments, and acts of faith and devotion, are reduced) and adore them with greateſt reverence, and are inflamed with ferventeſt devotion unto them. And therefore we may conclude that this confidence, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſneſſe, and fervour, proceedeth from hence, that theſe men, and ſuch among them as cannot be ſuſpected for ſimplicity, ignorance, or ſiniſter ends, are thus confirmed in this faith, and are thus ſet on fire with this devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more vigorouſly and vehemently then ordinary ſecular men; by the immediate working and inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt; from whoſe ſtreames it is likely they drinke purer and clearer waters, and nearer the well head, then other men of a more worldly and vulgar converſation. And it were not agreeable to the goodneſſe of God to permitt thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that moſt affectionatly ſeeke him, and who for his ſake out of pure devotion and deſire of contemplating truth, doe abridge themſelves of all other worldly contentments, to have their underſtanding worſe blinded with falſe doctrine then other men that ſeeke him more coldly and care leſſe for him; and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170053:77"/>to have their wills more depraved then theirs with erroneous and falſe devotion, as of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity it would follow theirs were, if the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine that the Catholicke Church profeſſeth were not true, and the holy Ghoſt reſided not in it to worke thoſe effects. Now on the contrary part, let us make a ſhort inquiry whether it be probable that the late pretended reformers have beene illuminated by God in an extraordinary manner, to diſcover truth: which they ſay hath for many ages lyen hidd. Surely if any ſuch thing were, they would have expreſſed in their manner of life by ſome extraordinary ſanctity and excellent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſupernaturall wiſdome, that extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary communication which they would perſwade us they had with the divinity. For as by a radiant beame of light ſhining in at the chinke of a window, we know aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Sunne beateth upon it, although we ſee not his body; ſo likewiſe there ſhould have broken out from them ſome admirable and excellent effect whereby we might reſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the divine Sunn illuminated their underſtanding, &amp; inflamed their Wil. Moyſes, when he came downe from the mountaine where he ſo long converſed with God, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed even by the luſter glittering from his face that it was not an ordinary or naturall
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170053:77"/>light which had ſhined unto him: the Apoſtles when they were repleniſhed with the holy Ghoſt, received immediately the gift of tongues, and a cleere intelligence of all the Scriptures; whereby they made cleere unto the auditors the obſcureſt paſſages of them; and continually wrought miracles. And all thoſe that ever ſince them have introduced the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell into any Countrey, where formerly it was not received, have ſtill had their commiſſion authoriſed by the ſame ſeales; and ſhall our late particular Reformers be credited in their pretended vocation, and in their new doctrine that ſhaketh the very foundations of the faith that hath beene by the whole Chriſtian world for ſo many ages believed and delivered over from hand to hand, when as nothing appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in them ſupernaturall, and proceeding from a divine cauſe?</p>
                  <p>This, Madame, is as much as I ſhall trouble your Ladyſhip withall upon this occaſion: which indeede is much more then at the firſt I intended, or could have ſuſpected my pen would have ſtolne from me. The ſubſtance of all which may be ſummed up, and reduced to this following ſhort queſtion; namely, whether in the election of the faith whereby you hope to be ſaved, you will be guided by the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent of the wiſeſt, the learned'ſt and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170053:78"/>the piouseſt men of the whole world, that have beene inſtructed in what they believe by men of the like quality living in the age before them, and ſo from age to age, untill the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Chriſt; and that in this manner have derived from the fountaine, both a perfect and full knowledge of all that ought to be believed; and likewiſe a right underſtanding and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Scriptures, as farr as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth faith; (the true ſence of which, ſo farr is alſo delivered over by the ſame tradition.) Or whether you will aſſent unto the new and wreſted interpretations of places of Scripture, made by late men, that rely meerely upon their ſingle judgement and witt (too ſlight a barke to ſayle in through ſo immenſe an Ocean) and whoſe chiefe leaders for human reſpects and ſiniſter ends (not to ſay worſe of them) made a deſperate defection from the other maine bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; ſince which time no two of them have agreed in doctrine; and among whom it is impoſſible your Ladyſhips great judgement and ſtrong underſtanding ſhould find any ſolid ſtay to rely ſecurely upon, and to quiet all thoſe rationall doubts that your perceiving witt ſuggeſteth unto you. And here Madame, I ſhall make an end; having ſincerely, and as ſuccinctly and plainely as I can, delivered you the chiefe conſiderations that in this affaire
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170053:78"/>turned the ſcale of the ballance with me; which in good faith I have done with all the ſimplicity and ingenuity that I can expreſſe my ſenſe with; being not at all warmed with any paſſion or partiality, nor raiſed out of my even pitch and temper with any ſpirit of diſputation, or ſiding humor; (which few have avoided upon this ſubject) but I have given you a true picture of my ſeriouſeſt and ſaddeſt thoughts &amp; reſolutions to my ſelfe in this moſt important buſineſſe; wherein you will believe I would take the greateſt pains I was able, to be ſure not to be deceived. I have not ſought to ſhew wittineſſe or acuteneſſe of learning in the debating of theſe points; or have affected poliſhed language in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them to paper; for this matter ſhould not be handled for oſtentation, but for uſe: and though peradventure if this diſcourſe ſhould fall into the view of ſome learned man, he may at the firſt ſight ſet but a ſlight valew upon it; yet I perſwade my ſelfe whoſoever he be, if he will ponder it ſeriouſly &amp; leaſurely, and with alike interiour recollection, as I at the firſt ſetl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the groundes of it in my owne ſoule, he will then find it toucheth the life of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and though I have not delivered my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions ſmoothly and well, yet he will not thinke his time loſt in reading them; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170053:79"/>ſtronger parts then I, hee will make cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er uſe of them then I have done. This I am ſure of; that although I have ſet this downe for your Ladyſhip, in two or three dayes (for it is not longer ſince you commanded me to doe it) yet it is the production and reſult of many howers meditations by my ſelfe; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſome yeeres: and how dry ſoever they may appeare to your Ladyſhip at the firſt; yet I dare promiſe you that upon your ſecond and third readings, and reflections upon them, they will gaine more credit with you; and you will (I know) by ſuch application of your thoughts upon them, enlarge and refine what dependeth of the maine heads, farr beyond any thing I have ſaid. For ſuch is the nature of notions that are wrought, like the ſilke wormes ball, of ones owne ſubſtance; they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford fine and ſtrong threads for a good work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to weave into a faire peece of ſtuffe: whereas they, that like bees doe gather hony from ſeverall authors, or that like Ants, doe make up their ſtore by what they picke up in the originall crude ſubſtance from others labours, may peradventure in their workes ſeeme more pleaſant at the firſt taſt, or appeare to have a fairer heape at the firſt view; but the others web is more uſefull, more ſubſtantiall, and more durable.</p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170053:79"/>
                  <p> I beſeech God of his grace and goodneſſe, in this life to enlighten your Ladyſhips un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that you may diſcerne truth, and to diſpoſe your will that you may imbrace it; and in the next, to give you part among thoſe glorious Apoſtles, Fathers, Doctors, and Martyrs, that deriving the ſame truth from him, have from hand to hand delivered it over to our times.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170053:80"/>
                  <head>The Table.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label> Of the utmoſt and higheſt perfection that it is poſſible for a man to arrive unto in this life. pag. 1.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 2.</label> How one may cleave, and intend wholy to Chriſt, deſpiſing all other things. p. 3.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 3.</label> In what the perfect conformity of man with God conſiſteth in this life. P. 6.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 4.</label> How our operations ought to be in the intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part of our ſoule onely, and not in our ſenſes. P. 8.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 5.</label> Of the purity of heart, which above all things is to be aymed at<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> P. 14.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 6.</label> That true devotion conſiſteth in adhering to God by the underſtanding, and will, depured from all commerce with materiall objects. P. 20.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 7.</label> In what manner ones heart is to be recollected within ones ſelfe. P. 24.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170053:80"/>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 8.</label> How, in all chances, a ſpirituall man ought to reſigne himſelfe to God. P. 29.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 9.</label> That the contemplation of God is to be preferred before all other exerciſes. P. 32.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 10.</label> That actuall and ſenſible devotion is not ſo much to be regarded, as to adhere to God with ones will. P. 38.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 11.</label> In what manner we are to reſiſt temptations, and to beare tribulations. P. 42.</item>
                     <item>CHAP. 12. Of the love of God, and of the great power it hath. P. 44.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 13.</label> Of the quality (and utility of prayer: and how ones heart is to be recollected within ones ſelfe. P. 49.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 14.</label> That in all judgements, we ought to reſort to the witneſſe of our conſciences. P. 52.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 15.</label> How the contempt of ones ſelfe may be cauſed in a man, and how profitable that is. p. 56.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. XVI.</label> How the Providence of God extendeth it ſelfe to all things. P. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
